<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Taleisin - Adventure Machine!</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://taleisin.com/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com" />
<updated>2017-05-07T07:02:55+12:00</updated>
<id>http://taleisin.com/</id>
<author>
  <name>Eben and Annie</name>
  <uri>http://taleisin.com/</uri>
  
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Email Issues]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/email-issues/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/email-issues</id>
  <published>2017-05-07T06:49:50+12:00</published>
  <updated>2017-05-07T06:49:50+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;It would appear that I messed up the email system with the last post. Hopefully
this issue will not re-occur in the future since I’ve added an automated check
before updating the blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not technical then you can stop reading now and click through at the
bottom of the email to previous post or click
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.taleisin.com/river-adventures/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re technical and care about what went wrong…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mailchimp cannot deal with relative urls in the rss feed. This means that
I have to tell Jekyll to use absolute urls. If I’m using absolute urls
I cannot test the blog on my local machine since the links all point to the live
site. I thought I had solved the issue by changing the config file with a script
before serving locally and deploying remotely. Clearly something went wrong in
the script (which works when I test it, you know the old “it works on my machine
excuse”). I’ve now added a condition to the deploy script to only deploy if the
absolute urls are present in the rss feed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory this should prevent broken links in emails going forward, but if 20+
years in IT has taught me anything… This too will be proven wrong in the
future.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/email-issues/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Email Issues here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on May 07, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[River Adventures]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/river-adventures/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/river-adventures</id>
  <published>2017-05-06T16:56:17+12:00</published>
  <updated>2017-05-06T16:56:17+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;A lot has happened since I’ve last written anything. This doesn’t mean that it’s
been boring…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, I’m not sure what  to write about since there’s so many awesome
adventures that we’ve had. The only logical  thing to do would be to write about
them in  the order they happened.  Given that watches and  calendars get ignored
aboard, we’ll just say that the following happened some time in February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We packed up the  possessions we wanted to keep and stored  them safely. We sold
everything worth selling and gave away  anything that we couldn’t sell. The rest
was sent off to the land fill. With the commitment made to live aboard full time
we got stuck  in the marina with some  bad weather. We had a date  to keep since
the CANANZ group were having a dinner  in Warkwarth and they were all planning a
cruise up the Mahurangi river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/32739029450/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;Annie Hill&amp;#x27;s fantail. We met Bryan and Linda (the current owners) this weekend we enjoyed a nice visit and beer with the aboard taleisin this afternoon.&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/3/2883/32739029450_1bfefb79c9_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;534&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;Annie Hill&amp;#x27;s fantail. We met Bryan and Linda (the current owners) this weekend we enjoyed a nice visit and beer with the aboard taleisin this afternoon.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We provisioned  Taleisin and played the  waiting game with the  weather and wind
gods. When ever  you’re supposed to be  somewhere at a certain time  and date it
seems impossible to get  good weather for it. Looking at the  light winds in the
forecast, we decided to leave a day earlier than required and hopefully make the
trip over two days instead of one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finally had a bit of wind so we cast the dock lines off and set sail! It took
us all  afternoon to make it  as far...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/river-adventures/&quot;&gt;Continue reading River Adventures here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on May 06, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Life Aboard Taleisin]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/life-aboard-taleisin/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/life-aboard-taleisin</id>
  <published>2017-02-16T10:16:07+13:00</published>
  <updated>2017-02-16T10:16:07+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since our last water based adventure. The reason we’ve been on
land for some time is so that we can avoid being on land for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/32547798620/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;Life aboard taleisin&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/4/3725/32547798620_bb3a55fdc7_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Life aboard taleisin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain. It’s now been a week and a half since Taleisin has been our only
home.  We  spent the  last  month  sorting through  all  our  stuff and  selling
everything  that is  surplus  to  requirement. The  rest  was  put into  storage
awaiting our  return some day  in the future. We  got the smallest  storage unit
that we  could get away  with and  really only stored  things that we  wanted to
store. This was challenging as it  forced us to go through absolutely everything
we own to ensure we’re not paying to store junk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we  surrendered the keys to  the rental house we  still had 2 car  loads of
stuff that we had to deal with. It was either coming with us onboard Taleisin or
we would  have to get  rid of it  since our storage unit  was full. I  guess you
could say that we’ve completely de-cluttered and paired down to the essentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few things we’ve learnt in the mean time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleisin is comfortable, and not  just comfortable for cruising, comfortable for
living. I  agree that 30 foot  is a small boat,  but she doesn’t feel  small. We
have had to adjust the way we do things, but it’s not been a huge hassle for us.
We’ve been living  at the dock without electricity, other  than that provided by
our 100  watt solar panel.  Honestly it’s not a  hardship, we love  the kerosene
lamps and  cooking with LPG (aka  propane) is a joy.  The ice box does  it’s job
well enough that we don’t miss the fridge. You can tell ...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/life-aboard-taleisin/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Life Aboard Taleisin here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on February 16, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Is It With Power Boats?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/what-is-it-with-power-boats/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/what-is-it-with-power-boats</id>
  <published>2017-01-18T19:31:07+13:00</published>
  <updated>2017-01-18T19:31:07+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been warned about this before,  cruising with a schedule doesn’t work. This
is more  true if you’re  sailing engine  less. While it’s  true that we  have an
outboard, we don’t carry that much petrol and when there’s a reasonable chop the
motor is not much use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We broke a  cardinal rule of cruising.  Whilst we’re both taking  a timeout from
work  at the  moment,  I’ve been  temporarily  sucked back  into  work for  some
important business deals to get closed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This unfortunate or  fortunate, depending on your perspective, fact  has lead to
us sailing back  to the marina in less than  favourable conditions. The schedule
dictated our  sailing day. Weather  plays an important  role in sailing  for us.
Since we’re still  learning we don’t like  to sail in conditions  that is beyond
our ability and comfort levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was looking  at the forecasts for days.  There was either too much  wind or no
wind. When I finally saw a forecast that looked like we might be able to sail in
the morning and get close to the marina, we started to plan our journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a  huge journey, it’s only  28 nautical miles to reach  the marina. The
forecasts called for 1 to 7 knots in  the morning with the wind dying down after
10am. The winds were shifting between SW., E. and NE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan was to get up early and sail for as long as we can. If we don’t make it
very far we can always anchor closer  and hopefully wait the weather out to make
it home on another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up at  6am. and got Taleisin ready to sail.  We skipped breakfast opting
to eat while under way. We weighed anchor and started motoring out of the river.
It was nice and calm, compared to the  previous day. I looked at the clock as we
were motoring out, it was 7am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we got out of the river I said  to Annie, lets get some sail up! We hoisted
the sails and the wind filled them. We  closed the throttle on the motor and put
it in neutral. That’s when the wind d...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/what-is-it-with-power-boats/&quot;&gt;Continue reading What Is It With Power Boats? here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 18, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Never Miss Another Adventure]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/never-miss-another-adventure/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/never-miss-another-adventure</id>
  <published>2017-01-18T17:44:33+13:00</published>
  <updated>2017-01-18T17:44:33+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;While this is not an adventure of  the nautical kind, I’ve just had an adventure
adding more dynamic content to a static  content only blog. If this doesn’t make
sense to you don’t worry about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important thing is that there’s now  a way for you to receive our adventures
directly via  email. While  this is not  my personal preference  I’ve had  a few
readers  ask for  this  feature.  Not wanting  to  disappoint  I quickly  hacked
something together to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re one of the readers wanting to receive emails with our adventures, type
your email address in the box below and subscribe to our mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/never-miss-another-adventure/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Never Miss Another Adventure here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 18, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Small Adventures]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/small-adventures/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/small-adventures</id>
  <published>2017-01-12T18:37:26+13:00</published>
  <updated>2017-01-12T18:37:26+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;When  you  own an  adventure  machine  like  Taleisin,  there’s no  shortage  of
adventures. After  our little adventure  with Taleisin  in Bon Accord  Harbor we
talked about the situation and what could have been done better. Sure, we didn’t
break  anything and  nobody got  injured,  but that  doesn’t mean  that we  were
comfortably in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discussed it with Lin, and she shed some light on what may have happened. Lin
suggested that  we take her little  12.5’ boat out for  a sail and go  and learn
what the winds do when you get closer to the headlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While waiting for  a bit more suitable  weather as the wind was  blowing quite a
bit and it was really gusty too! We  just kicked back and relaxed. We did have a
day where we went walking on the other side of North Cove. It truly is a magical
island. It’s  not in any way  related to the  timeline we’re used to.  It really
feels like  time has moved on  and this little island  is stuck in the  past. We
absolutely love this place!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday the  winds was a  bit more favourable  and Lin took  us out for  a few
minutes in Felicity. She showed us the ropes so to speak and then we headed back
to the dock.  Lin sent us off on our  way and we spent the better  part of a few
hours out  there tacking  back and  forth into the  wind. We  gybed all  the way
around to see how that would affect things and we got close the headlands to see
how the  winds shifted. Doing this  is a small  boat is a lot  less intimidating
since running  aground means that you  can hop out  (she only draws 3  feet) and
push  her off.  Fending is  also a  lot easier  as she  weighs a  lot less  than
Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/32112616382/in/photostream/&quot; title=&quot;Taken by Lin Pardey all copyright belongs to Lin Pardey. Published with permission.&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/358/32112616382_a0f7da1c5d_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Taken by Li...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/small-adventures/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Small Adventures here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 12, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rookie Mistake]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/rookie-mistake/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/rookie-mistake</id>
  <published>2017-01-08T18:33:23+13:00</published>
  <updated>2017-01-08T18:33:23+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;With the weather  turning and the anchorage getting less  comfortable we decided
to  find a  better spot.  We spent  the  last few  days carrying  water back  to
Taleisin. We did it the hard way, we  carried 20 Litre water cans back and forth
for a  total of  4 trips. We  rowed back and  forth and  loaded it all  on board
Taleisin. Yes we probably could have motored up to the dock and done it all very
quickly. That all sounded  too easy so we did it the hard  way. We got some good
exercise and I’m sure we’re better off because of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We  got Taleisin  ready to  sail  this morning.  We checked  and double  checked
everything. We put  a reef in the  main as it’s blowing around  17 knots gusting
into the  20’s. We  hoisted the main,  but didn’t cleat  the sheet  off. Feeling
confident we started to winch the anchor in, it’s a tough job if you’re not used
to it. I feel  like we’ll be better off physically in the  long run doing things
this way, rather than  the alternative. Time will tell if this gets easier or
more painful…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We soon had the  anchor weighed and started to slowly sail.  Annie said, I think
we’re actually  moving backward.  No problem  I’ll hoist  the stays’l.  With the
stays’l up we were going in the right direction! Great, we sailed off the anchor
again. This  time in a  bit more  breeze than before.  We didn’t even  start the
engine so we felt pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were short tacking up  the harbour as the wind was on the  nose. It was a bit
of trial and  error as we have  to backwind the stays’l to  ensure that Taleisin
brings her nose around properly. It probably  didn’t look to good from the shore
side, but we didn’t  care. We were sailing out of this  anchorage when most were
motoring. I’ll take that as a small victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had, what I thought,  a clean line to sail out of the  harbour. So I kept the
course I  was steering.  Then things  changed a  little and  I recall  saying to
Annie. We’re too close to the headland,...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/rookie-mistake/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Rookie Mistake here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 08, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Off Grid]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/off-grid/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/off-grid</id>
  <published>2017-01-06T20:12:58+13:00</published>
  <updated>2017-01-06T20:12:58+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;We’re back floating! The last couple of days have been fairly laid back, sure we
did  some work  on Taleisin.  Double  checking the  hull is  clean, making  sure
everything is removed behind the rudder. She’s looking pretty sweet! While I was
at it,  I got Lin  to supervise me  replacing the Sikaflex  on a few  small deck
seams. Whilst  it’s not rocket  science, there was a  few things I  didn’t know.
It’s always silly  in my eyes to not  learn from those around you  before you go
experimenting and  trying to work  out how to  do something that’s  already been
done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/32135639085/&quot; title=&quot;Off grid&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c6.staticflickr.com/1/658/32135639085_49dd06f5bd_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Off grid&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning  we decided  to sail around  to the Kawau  boating club,  seeing as
we’re  newly joined  members we  get some  benefits from  membership, like  free
showers, laundry and water. We needed all three of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We attempted to  sail off the mooring  in North Cove, but the  temptation of the
motor  was too  great. The  wind was  light  and it  seemed like  we were  going
backwards. We only had a short sail around the corner though…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used  the outboard  to get out  of North  Cove and caught  some wind.  It was
really annoying  me that  we used  the motor  and it  felt like  we gave  up too
easily. So  we sailed under  full canvas around the  corner and into  Bon Accord
Harbour. Since I  still had the sour taste  in my mouth from using  the motor, I
was determined to get a win today even if it’s just a small one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said to  Annie, we’re going to sail  past the boat club under  full sail, turn
around and  come back to  anchor. For bonus points  since it’s not  blowing that
hard, lets try to do it under sail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we  had our plan, we  were r...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/off-grid/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Off Grid here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 06, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Back on the Grid]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/back-on-the-grid/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/back-on-the-grid</id>
  <published>2017-01-04T07:41:34+13:00</published>
  <updated>2017-01-04T07:41:34+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Back on the tidal  grid! Since Taleisin is home and she still  fits on the tidal
grid at Lin’s we decided that it would be a good idea to give the bottom a clean
and inspect the seacock that’s been giving me grief as of late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/31241590584/in/photostream/&quot; title=&quot;Untitled&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/294/31241590584_5eeb16ef27_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Untitled&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got  the motor  going and  took Taleisin for  a trip  around the  bay, mostly
because the wind was blowing and we weren’t comfortable taking the direct route.
We navigated our way through all the moored boats and slowly made our way to the
jetty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I  followed Larry’s  advice: “Don’t  go any  faster than  you’re willing  to hit
something”. We came  into the dock very  slow and Annie climbed  off and grabbed
the stern line. I  had already placed the motor in neutral and  got ready to hop
off to  grab the bow line.  Then we heard  a loud crack. Whoops,  something must
have gone wrong!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the fenders got caught on one  of the cross braces and it snapped the end
off where  the nail went  through. As  a consequence I’ve  now got to  fix Lin’s
jetty. It  was a case of  just putting enough  pressure on just the  right spot.
Luckily Lin wasn’t upset with us so once we fix it, it will be all good again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We  walked Taleisin  onto the  grid and  Lin came  to double  check that  we got
everything just right. Then it was time to wait for the tide to go out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were  invited to a BBQ  at 5pm and  low tide was  at 5pm. So not  wasting any
time, I just got to the task as soon as I could wade into the water and give her
a good scrub down. It was a lot easier  this time. There was no tears and we got
the job done before 5pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/back-on-the-grid/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Back on the Grid here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 04, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Baking Bread]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/baking-bread/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/baking-bread</id>
  <published>2017-01-02T17:45:19+13:00</published>
  <updated>2017-01-02T17:45:19+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Today I baked  a loaf of bread. Very  exciting, I know. It’s been  almost a week
since we consumed our  last bread and I’ve been promising Annie  that I’d bake a
loaf of bread. It’s something I used to do a few years ago so the concept is not
new to me. How ever I’ve never done it all by hand without electricity. It’s not
rocket science to bake bread. Yeast, a bit  of sugar, water and flour with a bit
of salt will be the job done. Use a bit of elbow grease and it’s not long before
you have something that resembles dough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardest part was figuring out how to get the oven on board Taleisin to do my
bidding. The actual baking  part took a bit longer, but I suspect  with a bit of
trial and error I’ll get the hang of it. The loaf actually came out pretty good.
We’ve just about eaten  half of it already. Having said all of  that, it took me
the better part of the day to do it. It’s the time waiting in between that takes
long, the work is minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/31999785536/&quot; title=&quot;Today I baked bread.&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/517/31999785536_b19dc69926_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Today I baked bread.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far our stay in North Cove is  wonderful, the locals are friendly and we keep
getting invited to hang out with them. I’m starting to feel a bit guilty because
I’m being so  lazy and not really doing  much. Our aim is to get  out sailing in
the next few days and maybe go practice anchoring in the next bay over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing to mention is that rowing Cheeky&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; is getting easier. We
deliberately left the outboard at home to force us to row and get better at it.
I’m sure over time this will not be an issue at all and we’ll be healthier for
it. One thing we have been doing is taking turns rowing. If I row out Annie will
row back. That way we both get p...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/baking-bread/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Baking Bread here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 02, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview - Hooked on Wooden Boats]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/interview-hooked-on-wooden-boats/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/interview-hooked-on-wooden-boats</id>
  <published>2017-01-01T10:09:36+13:00</published>
  <updated>2017-01-01T10:09:36+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Looking at the  date, 2016 is finally over.  I believe a lot of  people would be
happy to see the back of 2016. Happy New Year, may 2017 be a good one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year when we were at the wooden  boat festival we did an interview with Dan
Mattson.  It was  a bit  of fun  and  Dan has  just sent  me the  word that  the
interview is up on his pod cast. If you’re curious have a listen
&lt;a href=&quot;http://hookedonwoodenboats.com/howb-191-interview-eben-bruyus-and-annie-ryan-on-acquiring-famed-cutter-taleisin-from-the-pardeys/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re still hanging out  in North Cove, we got invited to a  small new years eve
gathering with  the locals. We had  a great time and  got to see parts  of North
Cove we’ve never seen before. This place  is magical. When we head over that way
again I’ll  be sure to take  some pictures. Thank  you to all the  residents for
making our time here very pleasurable!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/interview-hooked-on-wooden-boats/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Interview - Hooked on Wooden Boats here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 01, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dinner Is Served]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/dinner-is-served/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/dinner-is-served</id>
  <published>2016-12-30T20:29:40+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-12-30T20:29:40+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Annie prepared  this magnificent meal  on board  Taleisin tonight. It  tasted as
good as it looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/31937747516/&quot; title=&quot;Dinner is served&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/433/31937747516_482ef6b63e_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Dinner is served&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After  a bit  of trial  and error  we figured  out how  to use  the oven  aboard
Taleisin. We did of  course have the benefit of being on a  mooring just a short
row from Lin’s door step. Lin is  always very helpful and knows everything about
anything aboard Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been  having a great time  in North Cove.  Lin invited us over  for dinner
along with the family on the French yacht next to us. Lin served what could only
be described as the best salmon I’ve  ever had. Everything is always lovely when
you’re over  for dinner at  the Pardey’s.  The company is  good and the  food is
always excellent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve had plenty of people come along  side Taleisin for a closer look. They are
always very friendly  and pleasant to have  a chat to. We’ve  been invited twice
already to  go visit some  friends along  one of the  beaches. We feel  a little
guilty as  we’ve been so lazy  that we haven’t made  it there yet. To  be honest
we’re probably just so exhausted from the rat race that we’re in need of all the
sleep we’ve been catching up on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today we decided to move to the correct mooring. Annie suggested that we
warp onto  the mooring as  it’s close by  and it would  be easier to  put backup
plans in place, than to start up the  outboard. The added bonus is that it would
be quiet and, not disturb any of the boats around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annie decided  that she would row  the warp out. We  attached a warp to  the old
mooring and to the stren, the warp Annie rowed out was attached to the bow. This
configuratio...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/dinner-is-served/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Dinner Is Served here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on December 30, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hanging Out in North Cove]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/hanging-out-in-north-cove/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/hanging-out-in-north-cove</id>
  <published>2016-12-28T19:10:05+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-12-28T19:10:05+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;We turned in  early last night, we  were both absolutely exhausted.  As an added
bonus we slept in this morning too. It’s  not like we have somewhere to be!? The
plan was to move Taleisin to a mooring closer to Lin’s place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we  finally decided to  wake up we  went on deck  and the cove  was nearly
empty. We were trying  to figure out which mooring we were  supposed to pick up.
After a bit of back and forth Annie suggested that we row over and check it out,
even tough it would be a right pain to row back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we were busy trying to get Cheeky off the cabin top a friendly sailor came
along side in a kayak and introduced herself.  We invited her on board for a bit
of a chat as it was quite choppy in  the spot we anchored. It turns out that her
boat was on the mooring next to the one  we were moving to. We asked her if she’d
mind helping us move. She was a real sport and jumped to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/31120073253/&quot; title=&quot;Hanging out in north cove&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c6.staticflickr.com/1/452/31120073253_585b6795bd_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Hanging out in north cove&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt bad putting her on the windlass as she wasn’t comfortable on the helm and
our cat does not like strangers so we  couldn’t give her the easy job of flaking
the chain into the  chain locker. I winched in most of the  chain as it’s really
hard work and  left the last bit to  her. Later she mentioned that  she was real
proud of herself  for using the manual windlass but  that she really appreciates
the electric windlass on her boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fairly uneventful apart from the fact that I still need to learn that the
wind affects the boats direction, so heading in the direction I want to go in is
not likely to be  the direction we’re actually going. The two  girls did a great
job fending off a power ...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/hanging-out-in-north-cove/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Hanging Out in North Cove here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on December 28, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Return to North Cove]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/return-to-north-cove/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/return-to-north-cove</id>
  <published>2016-12-27T19:27:34+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-12-27T19:27:34+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Our original  plan was  to sail to  North Cove yesterday.  But the  winds didn’t
co-operate, instead we motored all day and tucked in for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it turns out  that it was quite a bouncy anchorage,  easily corrected with a
snubber off  the bowsprit. Whilst  this didn’t stop the  bounce it made  it more
than habitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning I said to Annie, “I want to sail off the anchor!”. We had the motor
in neutral, just in  case. I  prepared Taleisin for  sailing while  Annie cooked
breakfast. After we finished eating and  putting Taleisin in order down below we
winched in the anchor until we were just  about ready to lift it. We hoisted the
stays’l. Annie grabbed the tiller and when  the anchor was up she sheeted in the
stays’l. We were off without a hitch! I hoisted the main and the jib while Annie
slowly sailed us out of the anchorage. It was a nice start to the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winds  were much better  today. We managed  to sail reasonably  smoothly all
day. Slight bit  of chop out in  the open water but nothing  like we experienced
when we sailed Taleisin to Westhaven the very firs time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we  approached North Cove a  little speed boat  zoomed right in front  of our
bow, I was  wondering why they were zooming  by so close and then  I realised it
was Lin in  Jay Dee. Lin took some  photos of us as we sailed  Taleisin into the
cove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We motored around looking  for a spot to anchor. I picked a  spot that I thought
look good. We dropped the anchor. Then Annie said, I think we’re dragging! Ok no
problem, we’ll try again. Winch the anchor in and motor around for a second try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We try it  again and same problem again!  Ok so this time we  weighed the anchor
and went further out than I would have  liked. We found a spot of clear water so
we can have lots of room. I drop the anchor. This time I’m not messing around we
put 35 fathoms of chain out! Now we’re holding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lin did  come by and offer  us a mooring  that’s ava...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/return-to-north-cove/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Return to North Cove here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on December 27, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Escape]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/escape/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/escape</id>
  <published>2016-12-26T17:10:15+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-12-26T17:10:15+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This might be  the post most of  the people following this little  blog has been
waiting for. Well maybe, we’re not heading  off shore, but we have cast the dock
lines off  for the  time being.  We’ve got  the boat  provisioned and  we’re out
playing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a little longer than  the previous weekend cruise we did (I haven’t
written about it yet, but it was  great). We’re currently sitting at anchor in a
small bay called Okoromai (Shakespeare) Bay.  We’re the only boat anchored here,
and there might be a reason for that we’re not sure yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our  plan  was to  sail  to  Kawau  Island today,  but  there  was no  wind,  so
unfortunately we had to use the noisy  outboard motor to get away from the dock.
The bottom line is that we’re out, away from the dock and we’re sailing! Well we
will be! We’ve decided to hang out in this little bay until the wind picks up so
we can continue our little journey to Kawau Island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s not much to  say about the adventure today as  it was rather uneventful.
We managed  to leave the marina  just fine, which of  course is a huge  bonus as
we’ve not had the best of luck with marina adventures to date! We managed to get
a  bit of  sailing done  in  the harbour  but  then the  winds died  completely.
Motoring is not fun  and we didn’t really care for it. It  was really a means to
an end,  now that we’ve left  the doc we don’t  feel the pressure of  needing to
leave. That part is done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that we’ve been  so busy with the run up to Christmas  we’re both tired so
now  it’s time  to rest  and recover  from all  the stress  we’ve placed  on our
bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are  some pictures  of the  little anchorage we’re  in. We’re  anchored in
about 4.5 meters of water and so far it would seem like a calm quite anchorage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/31763627521/&quot; title=&quot;Escape&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/1/368/31763627521_821a659ba6_c.jpg&quot; wid...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/escape/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Escape here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on December 26, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Port Townsend Wooden Boat Festival 2016]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/port-townsend-wooden-boat-festival-2016/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/port-townsend-wooden-boat-festival-2016</id>
  <published>2016-10-31T16:08:31+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-10-31T16:08:31+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Our  recent status  as  wooden boat  owners  has  opened up  many  new doors  to
interested and exciting  opportunities. We are not only new  to wooden boats but
to boats and sailing itself. One evening after completing one of many boat tasks
I gave  Lin Pardey a call  to share my  experiences. Lin suggested that  we come
along to the  wooden boat festival in Port Townsend  Washington State, USA. This
presented numerous challenges concerning work for  both Annie and myself. When I
got home that evening I told Annie about this random spur of the moment idea and
we decided that life is too short, screw it - lets do it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/30222678904/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;DSC_6140&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5692/30222678904_d7ccb6bd84_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;531&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_6140&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/30738394322/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;DSC_6117&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5464/30738394322_9250be565e_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;531&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_6117&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I distinctly remember Annie asking, “What will I be doing for three whole days”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to September 6 2016, we’re on our way to Port Townsend via Seattle.
This is one of  the routes into Port Townsend. In order to  get to Port Townsend
you  really want  to have  to get  there. Driving  from Seattle  takes 2  hours,
getting there by  public transport is quite  a feat in itself.  Our journey from
Seattle started early  in the morning taking  the train from our  hotel close to
the SeaTac  airport. A short walk  from down town  Seattle to a 30  minute ferry
ride. Once off the  Ferry we caught a bus to Poulsbo, then  we spent the bulk of
the day in Poulsbo  wai...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/port-townsend-wooden-boat-festival-2016/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Port Townsend Wooden Boat Festival 2016 here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on October 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why a 20 hp Outboard]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/why-a-20hp-outboard/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/why-a-20hp-outboard</id>
  <published>2016-08-08T14:58:17+12:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-08T14:58:17+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;After some discussions on forums, it became obvious that I’d have to do a follow
up post on why I got a 20 hp. Honda motor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a few variables that went into the equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weight, Cost and Horsepower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked at  the Torqeedo 4 kw motor. That  in theory was a good idea,  8 hp. in
cruise  mode, 10  hp. thrust  (which incidentally  Lin and  Larry said  would be
enough).  This motor  is about  20 kg.  Then comes  the batteries.  The Torqeedo
batteries are 24.3 kg. each, you  require 2. These batteries are very expensive,
so going with a lead-acid/AGM option you’d  need 4 x 200 A/H batteries (Torqeedo
batteries  are 24V  lithium).  Finding  space for  these  batteries  would be  a
challenge in it’s  own right. Not to  mention that the costs would  be very high
for a  setup like  this and  charging would be  a challenge  unless you’re  in a
marina. Even then  it’s very easy to add  petrol to a tank, start  the motor and
go. Not  the same with batteries.  This is also  not a simple setup,  it’s quite
complicated and at odds with the rest  of the boat. Incidentally I looked at the
10 kw motor too, that weighs 64kg and requires twice as many batteries, so twice
the problem.  Not to  mention 3  times the cost  without installation  costs and
brackets etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the other option is to go  for petrol. I wanted something that’s simple, that
means manual tilt, tiller steer and pull start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yamaha  9.9 hp. has been  mentioned, I rejected  that motor due to  the fact
that it’s  electric start  only (battery and  more complication  required), this
motor also  weights 49 -  52KG depending on  the model. So  not a lot  of upside
here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tohatsu is another one that was mentioned. The dealers proved challenging to get
a quote from,  at first. This lead me  to wonder what support would  be like, if
they are in sales  mode they are at their best, so they  won’t get any better…
The motor  that was quoted was  not only 20%  more e...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/why-a-20hp-outboard/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Why a 20 hp Outboard here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on August 08, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Training Wheels]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/training-wheels/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/training-wheels</id>
  <published>2016-07-31T10:59:23+12:00</published>
  <updated>2016-07-31T10:59:23+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;When we first  bought Taleisin we considered getting an  outboard mounted on the
transom. We even got  a boat builder out in the first couple  of weeks of having
her in  the marina. If  you’re familiar with Taleisin  you’ll know that  she was
built and designed to hate motors. Nothing  is easy with Taleisin, simple is not
easy. Luckily I love a good challenge!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many talks with a lot of different people I finally came to the conclusion
that I’m not likely to get a motor mounted on Taleisin. If you’ve been following
this blog you’ll be aware of my defeat  in the marina with Ducky on the quarter.
Not  my finest  moment, but  I’m  sure it  was  entertaining to  many. I’ve  had
suggestions of  putting a  well in the  lazaret (with a  plywood box),  I’ve had
suggestions  of sacrificing  the sits  tub for  an inboard  engine. I’ve  always
listened and considered things,  but honestly when people tell me  to put a hole
in Taleisin they normally  lose me. The day will come when I  finally put a hole
in her somewhere, but not yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent many  hours researching motors, electric and  conventional. I’ve made
new friends on  the internet while doing  this. I looked at  inboard options and
outboard options. I  looked at electric pod motors, electric  trolling motors. I
did thought experiments with these different types of motors. I calculated costs
vs benefits. Weight, practicality and anything  else I could think of. I thought
about different ways to mount the motor, using existing chainplates and rigging,
mounting it on  the rudder, hanging it  from the bumpkin on  a cantilever. Where
would holes  need to be  made in order  to make it  viable. I considered  a side
mounted motor, but rejected that idea because when I had Ducky on the quarter it
was very hard to get steerage as low speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always at some  point I’d stop and  ask myself, what’s the objective?  What am I
trying to  achieve with all of  this. The answer  is never, to give  Talei...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/training-wheels/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Training Wheels here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on July 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Pick at It, You'll Only Make It Worse]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/dont-pick-at-it-youll-only-make-it-worse/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/dont-pick-at-it-youll-only-make-it-worse</id>
  <published>2016-07-11T14:00:27+12:00</published>
  <updated>2016-07-11T14:00:27+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Haul out day has arrived. When we  spent a day scrubbing Taleisin before we took
delivery of her, Annie told me that we’ll have to haul her out and sand her down
properly. As  always I should just  listen to Annie,  but that would be  far too
easy, it’s a much better idea to charge off and learn lessons the hard way…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While talking to my father on the phone I mentioned that I might buy him a plane
ticket from Australia to come and give me a hand - I was only kidding as I would
never put him to  work against his will. A couple of days  later my father calls
me up, asking when  Taleisin is coming out of the water as  he’s coming over and
give me a hand. Great I’ll have extra  hands to do more work. Annie’s father was
due in  New Zealand  shortly after and  he is  always keen to  lend a  hand with
anything  that  resembles  work.  There’s  a  lot  to  be  said  for  the  older
generation’s willingness to work, no matter  how soul destroying or miserable it
might be. So I started to make a list (oh how naive I was in my younger days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mum and dad arrived the day before haul out. Annie was away on school camp for a
few days so I was  holding down the fort - well as much  as can be expected when
people are foolish enough  to leave me in charge. In my  infinite wisdom I ended
up booking the  haul out during the  biggest classic boat regatta  in Auckland -
Taleisin should have been part of it.  Never mind, it’s booked people are coming
to  help so  I’m locked  in. We’ll  be back  in the  water before  long, 2  long
weekends should  be more  than enough  and with many  hands to  help it  will go
quick!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haul out was  much less adventurous than  I imagined it to be.  We simply walked
Taleisin  into the  cradle  and had  a  couple  of attempts  to  get her  seated
properly. I  probably drove the guys  in the boat  yard nuts as I  was concerned
at  every  step of  the  process.  Who wouldn’t  be,  a  boat like  Taleisin  in
irreplaceable. A big thank...
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/dont-pick-at-it-youll-only-make-it-worse/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Don&#39;t Pick at It, You&#39;ll Only Make It Worse here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on July 11, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guest Blog  Post at  the Unlikely  Boat Builder]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://taleisin.com/guest-blog-post-at-the-unlikely-boat-builder/" />
  <id>http://taleisin.com/guest-blog-post-at-the-unlikely-boat-builder</id>
  <published>2016-04-29T12:57:58+12:00</published>
  <updated>2016-04-29T12:57:58+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri>http://taleisin.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I’ve written a post. I’ve been quite snowed under with a
lot of different projects and my mind was refusing to co-operate. I was asked by
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unlikelyboatbuilder.com/&quot;&gt;John Almberg&lt;/a&gt;  to write  a guest  post for
his blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably of interest to everybody who’s following us. I wrote about why we&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;bought Taleisin. You can read the post &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unlikelyboatbuilder.com/2016/04/why-did-you-buy-taleisin.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com/guest-blog-post-at-the-unlikely-boat-builder/&quot;&gt;Continue reading Guest Blog  Post at  the Unlikely  Boat Builder here.&lt;/a&gt; Originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;http://taleisin.com&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on April 29, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
