<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Taleisin - Adventure Machine!</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2016-12-26T17:34:22+13:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Eben and Annie</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Escape]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/escape/" />
  <id>/escape</id>
  <published>2016-12-26T17:10:15+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-12-26T17:10:15+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This might be  the post most of  the people following this little  blog has been
waiting for. Well maybe, we’re not heading  off shore, but we have cast the dock
lines off  for the  time being.  We’ve got  the boat  provisioned and  we’re out
playing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a little longer than  the previous weekend cruise we did (I haven’t
written about it yet, but it was  great). We’re currently sitting at anchor in a
small bay called Okoromai (Shakespeare) Bay.  We’re the only boat anchored here,
and there might be a reason for that we’re not sure yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our  plan  was to  sail  to  Kawau  Island today,  but  there  was no  wind,  so
unfortunately we had to use the noisy  outboard motor to get away from the dock.
The bottom line is that we’re out, away from the dock and we’re sailing! Well we
will be! We’ve decided to hang out in this little bay until the wind picks up so
we can continue our little journey to Kawau Island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s not much to  say about the adventure today as  it was rather uneventful.
We managed  to leave the marina  just fine, which of  course is a huge  bonus as
we’ve not had the best of luck with marina adventures to date! We managed to get
a  bit of  sailing done  in  the harbour  but  then the  winds died  completely.
Motoring is not fun  and we didn’t really care for it. It  was really a means to
an end,  now that we’ve left  the doc we don’t  feel the pressure of  needing to
leave. That part is done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that we’ve been  so busy with the run up to Christmas  we’re both tired so
now  it’s time  to rest  and recover  from all  the stress  we’ve placed  on our
bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are  some pictures  of the  little anchorage we’re  in. We’re  anchored in
about 4.5 meters of water and so far it would seem like a calm quite anchorage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/31763627521/&quot; title=&quot;Escape&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/1/368/31763627521_821a659ba6_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Escape&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/31070853873/in/photostream/&quot; title=&quot;Escape&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/1/526/31070853873_0d6be758ed_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Escape&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/31842745676/in/photostream/&quot; title=&quot;Escape&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/256/31842745676_8f8bfd1573_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Escape&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/31763620081/&quot; title=&quot;Escape&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/1/339/31763620081_3842fd3f3c_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;Escape&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/escape/&quot;&gt;Escape&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on December 26, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Port Townsend Wooden Boat Festival 2016]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/port-townsend-wooden-boat-festival-2016/" />
  <id>/port-townsend-wooden-boat-festival-2016</id>
  <published>2016-10-31T16:08:31+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-10-31T16:08:31+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Our  recent status  as  wooden boat  owners  has  opened up  many  new doors  to
interested and exciting  opportunities. We are not only new  to wooden boats but
to boats and sailing itself. One evening after completing one of many boat tasks
I gave  Lin Pardey a call  to share my  experiences. Lin suggested that  we come
along to the  wooden boat festival in Port Townsend  Washington State, USA. This
presented numerous challenges concerning work for  both Annie and myself. When I
got home that evening I told Annie about this random spur of the moment idea and
we decided that life is too short, screw it - lets do it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/30222678904/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;DSC_6140&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5692/30222678904_d7ccb6bd84_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;531&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_6140&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/30738394322/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;DSC_6117&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5464/30738394322_9250be565e_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;531&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_6117&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I distinctly remember Annie asking, “What will I be doing for three whole days”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to September 6 2016, we’re on our way to Port Townsend via Seattle.
This is one of  the routes into Port Townsend. In order to  get to Port Townsend
you  really want  to have  to get  there. Driving  from Seattle  takes 2  hours,
getting there by  public transport is quite  a feat in itself.  Our journey from
Seattle started early  in the morning taking  the train from our  hotel close to
the SeaTac  airport. A short walk  from down town  Seattle to a 30  minute ferry
ride. Once off the  Ferry we caught a bus to Poulsbo, then  we spent the bulk of
the day in Poulsbo  waiting for one of 2 buses to Port  Townsend, one at 9am and
one at 5pm. We  didn’t do our homework properly and weren’t  quite aware of this
fact…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually we made our  way into Port Townsend late in  the afternoon. We walked
from the bus stop to our accommodation. Everybody in town was very friendly, the
homeless people  sleeping in the  park were greeting us  as we walked  past. The
feel of the town was worlds apart from the busy city. Port Townsend truly is the
hidden gem of the pacific north west.  Our hosts drove us into town that evening
for dinner. It’s worth noting that we have never met them before. They were kind
enough  to put  us  up for  the  duration of  the festival  at  no charge.  It’s
important  to note  that  if  you’re planning  on  attending  the festival  that
accommodation books out a year in advance,  plan well ahead and book very early.
After dinner I had to  use a bit of slight of hand so  that I could actually pay
the bill, our hosts were being too kind to us. This was only the start of a very
warm reception in this wonderful town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning  our hosts sent me a  text message to inform me  that they have
left us passes  for the festival which will  get us in, free of  charge. This is
generally not  the sort of thing  we’re used to.  We stayed close enough  to the
festival grounds  so that we  could walk.  We set off  early in the  morning and
there was a  bit of a chill in the  air. By the time we reached  the festival it
was nice and warm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festival is held in the marina on the edge of town. There are over 300 boats
packed  in like  sardines. The  harbour master  did a  fantastic job.  The boats
ranged from large steamers and schooners  to small row boats, beautiful stand up
paddle boards  and kayaks. If  there was a  way to build it  out of wood  and it
floated you could find it there. This might sound strange but there were so many
beautiful boats  that it all got  lost in the  abundance. It was really  hard to
appreciate each  individual boat with so  many around it. The  docks were filled
with enthusiasts  of all  ages. It didn’t  take long before  we were  invited to
board vessels,  with proud owners showing  off their baby. We  could spend hours
talking to one owner  and looking at just one boat. Unfortunately  we only had 3
days to see as many of the 300 odd boats as we could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/30818279046/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;DSC_6147&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5760/30818279046_c48db1aa02_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;531&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_6147&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With so  many boats around,  and so many  Kiwi’s, there was  bound to be  a Kiwi
boat. Heather  is a 37 footer  built in Auckland  in 1937. She completed  a solo
circumnavigation in  the mid  60’s and  sailed to  Hawaii in  the 70’s,  now she
resides in Port Townsend. It was great to see a little bit of home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/30222706544/in/photolist-N3FgHj-N3Fgi1-N3FfpC-N3FfSw-N3Fe8E-N3FdvC-NQfCUQ-NQfAT5-NQfAnL-NQfzPS-N3o7hP&quot; title=&quot;DSC_6165&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5598/30222706544_dd4865ba9f_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;531&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_6165&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given  the amount  of boats  it became  quite  clear that  3 days  would not  be
enough, to  add to the  challenge there  were multiple seminars  being presented
simultaneously throughout the entire festival. It was impossible to choose which
seminars to attend and which to skip. They were all very well presented and full
of incredibly useful information. If you were  that way inclined you could get 3
days worth of value out of just  attending seminars. While all of this is taking
place there’s a bunch of teams building wooden boats for the competition that is
held over  the three days. We  were so busy that  we never got to  see the final
results. We  managed to have one  walk by to  inspect the progress on  the first
day. We spent some time in the  seminars, all the seminars we attended were well
presented and has something of value in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our hosts put on a fantastic BBQ for  some of us Kiwis, we spent the whole night
having a great  time with all the new  friends we made. While at the  BBQ it was
suggested that we try to get onboard  for the schooner racing. We spent the next
morning trying to find  a boat to crew on. We were  not successful, barefoot Bob
to the rescue! We met Bob at the BBQ our hosts put on for the Kiwis, he’s a very
colourful character with  a great sense of  humour. Bob found us  a spot onboard
Sassafrass, the  owners were very friendly  and we had a  blast. There’s nothing
quite like experiencing these wonderful boats  out on the water under full sail!
This took up the entire afternoon, while  it cost us valuable time we could have
used looking at boats at the docks. This experience was well worth the cost!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/30553738340/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;DSC_6078&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5643/30553738340_42a4946780_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;263&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_6078&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that was not enough, the town  is littered with antique shops and second hand
bookshops. This  is another favourite of  ours, we only managed  2 bookshops and
one antique shop, it was huge, the biggest antique shop we’ve ever been in. This
alone made us wish we had 3 weeks to spend in this wonderful town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/30553896060/in/album-72157674832493471/&quot; title=&quot;DSC_6236&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5694/30553896060_5025e1b862_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;531&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_6236&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To top the experience off there were all  kinds of toys and eye candy for boats.
Almost anything  imaginable for wooden boats.  The foundry had a  display of the
wonderful goodies  they can  make for  your boat.  Authors selling  their books,
tools,  tools and  more  tools. If  you’re  a  lover of  wooden  boats, this  is
certainly the place to  be. I recommend you come for the  festival, but stay for
the town and it’s wonderful people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festival  closes with the  most spectacular event.  All the boats  leave the
marina and  sail up and  down the  harbour so that  everybody can see  them from
shore. I have never  in my life seen so many beautiful wooden  boats sail at the
same time. There were  classics as far as the eye could see.  To quote a friend,
“You can’t beat the classics!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/30219451333/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;DSC_6247&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5797/30219451333_f2200f7499_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;531&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_6247&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned earlier that there’s only 2  buses in and out of Port Townsend. This
left us  with a  bit of  a dilemma.  Since I  didn’t do  my homework  and booked
flights out of SeaTac  for 9am on Monday, this meant we would  have to leave the
festival at 4pm on Sunday to catch the  bus at 5pm back to Seattle and spend the
night at the airport. When I started  to ask around if there was anybody leaving
super early on Monday  morning so we could catch the 6am  ferry (2 hours drive),
barefoot Bob came to our rescue. Bob is  a Port Townsend local, he’s got a heart
of gold. He  asked around, since he  was working with the harbour  master he was
talking to lots of  people. He came up empty handed, but  in the most unexpected
bit  of kindness  he offered  to drive  us  to the  ferry at  4am himself.  This
illustrates just how  kind the people in  this little town are. Bob  made an off
the cuff  comment that this  is what  they do in  Port Townsend. I  believe him,
everybody was awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suffice to  say we made the  journey on Monday  morning and caught our  plane to
Boston without any drama. A special  thanks to barefoot Bob, Brion and Christian
for making our  stay in Port Townsend very special  and something we’ll remember
for the rest of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ever  find yourself in Port  Townsend, find barefoot Bob!  Buy him lunch,
dinner or a beer. This will give you an excuse to meet him, he is awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS. If you’re looking for more pictures check out my collection over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/albums/72157674832493471&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/port-townsend-wooden-boat-festival-2016/&quot;&gt;Port Townsend Wooden Boat Festival 2016&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on October 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why a 20 hp Outboard]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/why-a-20hp-outboard/" />
  <id>/why-a-20hp-outboard</id>
  <published>2016-08-08T14:58:17+12:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-08T14:58:17+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;After some discussions on forums, it became obvious that I’d have to do a follow
up post on why I got a 20 hp. Honda motor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a few variables that went into the equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weight, Cost and Horsepower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked at  the Torqeedo 4 kw motor. That  in theory was a good idea,  8 hp. in
cruise  mode, 10  hp. thrust  (which incidentally  Lin and  Larry said  would be
enough).  This motor  is about  20 kg.  Then comes  the batteries.  The Torqeedo
batteries are 24.3 kg. each, you  require 2. These batteries are very expensive,
so going with a lead-acid/AGM option you’d  need 4 x 200 A/H batteries (Torqeedo
batteries  are 24V  lithium).  Finding  space for  these  batteries  would be  a
challenge in it’s  own right. Not to  mention that the costs would  be very high
for a  setup like  this and  charging would be  a challenge  unless you’re  in a
marina. Even then  it’s very easy to add  petrol to a tank, start  the motor and
go. Not  the same with batteries.  This is also  not a simple setup,  it’s quite
complicated and at odds with the rest  of the boat. Incidentally I looked at the
10 kw motor too, that weighs 64kg and requires twice as many batteries, so twice
the problem.  Not to  mention 3  times the cost  without installation  costs and
brackets etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the other option is to go  for petrol. I wanted something that’s simple, that
means manual tilt, tiller steer and pull start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yamaha  9.9 hp. has been  mentioned, I rejected  that motor due to  the fact
that it’s  electric start  only (battery and  more complication  required), this
motor also  weights 49 -  52KG depending on  the model. So  not a lot  of upside
here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tohatsu is another one that was mentioned. The dealers proved challenging to get
a quote from,  at first. This lead me  to wonder what support would  be like, if
they are in sales  mode they are at their best, so they  won’t get any better…
The motor  that was quoted was  not only 20%  more expensive than the  Honda but
also weighed 62 kg. It’s worth noting  that this was a manual/electric start and
also a manual/power tilt - which explains the weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honda, I looked at  the 8/10 hp which is the same  motor just tuned differently,
this was 48 kg. The 15/20 hp. which  is the same motor just tuned differently at
52 kg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the only motors I’ll mention as inboards were not an option due to the
required hole(s) in the hull. Other manufacturers didn’t do 25” shafts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end  of the day the weight  vs benefit ration landed me with  Honda 20 hp
25” shaft, of course the dealer was fantastic too so that helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick  note on electric  inboards. The cost of  the motor and  batteries would
have been 3  times the total of  the outboard solution. I didn’t  even bother to
cost the installation  of it. It was  considered as a hypothetical  case, but it
was never really  an option. This of  course comes with the problem  of where to
store all those batteries. The same goes for electric POD motors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking all of the  above and possibly a lot of things I  forgot about, it seemed
that the sensible choice would be to go for 20 hp. over 8 hp. for a 4 kg. weight
increase. The option to  go with a smaller engine is always  there too, not that
you gain much by going smaller, maybe if I  went for a 5 hp. motor it might have
made a noticeable difference in weight. Taleisin is 8 tons when empty, the 8 hp.
on the rubber  ducky does the job but  leaves a lot to be  desired and certainly
wont stop her in a  hurry if it’s needed. I learnt that the  hard way when I got
defeated in the marina (see the post about it).&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/why-a-20hp-outboard/&quot;&gt;Why a 20 hp Outboard&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on August 08, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Training Wheels]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/training-wheels/" />
  <id>/training-wheels</id>
  <published>2016-07-31T10:59:23+12:00</published>
  <updated>2016-07-31T10:59:23+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;When we first  bought Taleisin we considered getting an  outboard mounted on the
transom. We even got  a boat builder out in the first couple  of weeks of having
her in  the marina. If  you’re familiar with Taleisin  you’ll know that  she was
built and designed to hate motors. Nothing  is easy with Taleisin, simple is not
easy. Luckily I love a good challenge!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many talks with a lot of different people I finally came to the conclusion
that I’m not likely to get a motor mounted on Taleisin. If you’ve been following
this blog you’ll be aware of my defeat  in the marina with Ducky on the quarter.
Not  my finest  moment, but  I’m  sure it  was  entertaining to  many. I’ve  had
suggestions of  putting a  well in the  lazaret (with a  plywood box),  I’ve had
suggestions  of sacrificing  the sits  tub for  an inboard  engine. I’ve  always
listened and considered things,  but honestly when people tell me  to put a hole
in Taleisin they normally  lose me. The day will come when I  finally put a hole
in her somewhere, but not yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent many  hours researching motors, electric and  conventional. I’ve made
new friends on  the internet while doing  this. I looked at  inboard options and
outboard options. I  looked at electric pod motors, electric  trolling motors. I
did thought experiments with these different types of motors. I calculated costs
vs benefits. Weight, practicality and anything  else I could think of. I thought
about different ways to mount the motor, using existing chainplates and rigging,
mounting it on  the rudder, hanging it  from the bumpkin on  a cantilever. Where
would holes  need to be  made in order  to make it  viable. I considered  a side
mounted motor, but rejected that idea because when I had Ducky on the quarter it
was very hard to get steerage as low speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always at some  point I’d stop and  ask myself, what’s the objective?  What am I
trying to  achieve with all of  this. The answer  is never, to give  Taleisin an
engine. The  answer is always to  facilitate learning and accelerate  our way up
the learning  cliff (that’s when the  curve goes up and  backwards). Taleisin is
not a beginners  boat, that means we  can’t take the usual  approach to learning
with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When  I got  completely and  utterly defeated  by Taleisin  in the  marina Annie
suggested that we get a mooring and try that approach first (I actually listened
that  time). It  worked and  we learnt  quite a  bit while  on the  mooring. The
reality though, we didn’t get out on Taleisin as much as we should have. Getting
to and from  the mooring was a  long and slow process. Keeping  the objective in
mind, this  was the  opposite. I’d be  lying if  I said that  I didn’t  drive by
Taleisin every time the weather was acting up, to check on her. I probably would
not be  able to do much  in the event that  something went wrong, but  I checked
none the less. Every storm I’d be  laying awake at night worrying about Taleisin
on the mooring (for the record, worrying does nothing but make you feel bad).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the seasons  changing, I said to  Annie we’re going back in  the marina for
winter. This  wasn’t a hard sell  as Annie must  have been concerned too.  So we
waited for a nice day to move Taleisin back into the marina. This of course left
us stuck in the marina again. I started on solving the motor challenge again. If
it’s easy  to come and go  from the marina, we’ll  use Taleisin a lot  more, and
we’ll learn faster!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the  same time Lin sent  me an email  saying that there’s some  people she
thinks we’d enjoy meeting, they live on their wooden boat around the corner from
Taleisin. I called Doug and went to his  boat Karie L. We hit it off immediately
and it  wasn’t long before I  started talking about  my idea for a  motor mount.
Doug was kind enough to help me with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doug produced a  lot of conceptual drawings which eventually  lead to the design
that’s now mounted on Taleisin’s bumpkin.
&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28733328515/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;Motor Mount 3&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8632/28733328515_9846eef82b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;571&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;Motor Mount 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28733334875/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;Motor Mount 1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7484/28733334875_5be22dbc9b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;571&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;Motor Mount 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28115679104/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1814&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8711/28115679104_8eb2e8c762_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1814&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doug made a pattern for the design and  we got it cast in bronze, I’m very happy
with the results!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28701183856/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1819&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8153/28701183856_1bda1ede0f_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1819&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The essence  of the mount  is a  length of teak  across the bumpkin,  behind the
rudder. This  is clamped onto  the bumpkin with 2  wooden blocks made  from teak
with bronze bolts through it on either side of the spruce timber of the bumpkin.
We’ve put  some rubber  padding between  the timbers to  protect it.  The bronze
casting slides over the timbers on the port side (in theory this is a reversible
bracket). Timber pads are glued on with sikaflex on the mounting plate, a couple
of rivets are also in place as a “just in case”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28117867283/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1821&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8451/28117867283_8f415a14b9_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1821&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28115698534/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1822&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8803/28115698534_5d217b18db_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1822&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28115699954/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1823&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8565/28115699954_7af2bac97c_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1823&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28628110962/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1824&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8714/28628110962_e0183a2e03_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1824&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We bought a 20HP Honda outboard. The motor has a 20” shaft, the dealer was great
and installed  a 5” spacer to  make this a 25”  shaft motor, none of  this works
without a 25” shaft motor!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28115697144/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1826&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8855/28115697144_6622b09035_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1826&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28115694764/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1828&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8810/28115694764_fc510fc07e_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1828&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a  bit of fun  and games we  eventually managed to  get the motor  onto the
bracket. The Leopard Seal in the marina came to investigate while we were at it,
it was likely the banging noise from riveting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started the motor up and had it  running in forward and reverse. I had always
known that there would be flex in  the mount if it’s not braced. Doug’s original
concept had a tie-rod  from the chain plate to the mounting  plate. It was clear
that this would be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point  rather than jumping in  and getting a tie-rod in  place I thought
I’d take  a step back and  play around with a  few different ideas first.  In my
original  idea there  was a  brace that  pushed up  against the  transom and  it
lashings to the  chain plate and taffrail.  While thinking about all  of this it
dawned on  me that  I didn’t  take shock loading  into consideration.  The motor
weighs 52kg.  Shock loading could  turn that  into 500kg static  load equivalent
without too  much effort (think gravity  when bouncing up and  down over waves).
Taking a wave against  the motor is another thing all together  - I haven’t even
started to think  about mitigating that scenario, other than  don’t get into the
situation in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28115686394/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1836&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8493/28115686394_562117be84_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1836&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28115685244/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1837&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8585/28115685244_53513008b5_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1837&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28115683694/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1839&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8353/28115683694_5b5a9ebde2_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1839&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my  thinking cap  went on again.  I decided  to get some  cheap timber  for a
prototype from the off-cuts bin at the local hardware store. I knocked something
up that’s  functional. I bolted it  on with 2 eye  bolts. I got some  Dyneema to
create rigging of some  sorts to keep the brace up against  the transom while in
forward and reverse. I added a couple  of turn buckles so I could tighten things
up. I  used a sewn webbing  sling with a larks  foot on the taffrail.  I added a
shackle between the sling and the Dyneema to avoid friction melting through both
(it’s very  scary how  easy this  is to do,  it’s something  I learnt  from rock
climbing). The shackle is tri-loaded which is not ideal, but I doubt it would be
the first point  of failure. One lashing is  around the brace to lift  it up and
wedge it in place  against the transom. The other is to  the eyebolt which takes
some of the motor load. This configuration gives me the triangle structure I was
after to create a strong support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rig serves 2  purposes. The first is that it stops  the mount flexing under
the motor’s torque.  The second is that  it transfers some of the  load from the
bumpkin to the taffrail for shock loading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all  of this  in place,  Paul, another  friend I  made because  of Taleisin
walked by on  Friday afternoon just as  I was finishing everything up.  He had a
quick look and thought it looked good. The  next thing he asked if I was keen to
give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we  prepped Taleisin for her  maiden voyage under  her own motor. We  came up
with a plan  and started to back  out. The sub-title of this  blog is “Adventure
Machine”, and this post would not be complete without some adventure…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We let the  mooring lines go and  start backing Taleisin out. Paul  asked if the
bowsprit was clear from  the pilings as we’re about to turn  into the fairway. I
said the bowsprit  was clear. Paul asked if  we were good to go,  and suddenly I
noticed that  the floating  line between  the bow and  stern mooring  lines were
caught on the lifelines. I ran to release it. It wasn’t possible as I had undone
the lifelines to get the motor on board and had tangled the floating line in the
process. This meant that we’re still attached to the dock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick, put her in forward, I yelled. We got Taleisin stopped so I could undo the
lifelines. Paul was up at the bow fending so that the wind wouldn’t blow us into
the launch next  to us. I got  the lifelines undone and released  us without too
much trouble. Disaster averted!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to getting Taleisin out. We backed out and were able to use the outboard as
a bit  of a  stern thruster by  turning it  with it’s tiller.  At this  point it
started to feel like cheating. It was actually easy moving Taleisin. We left the
fairway without any issue. The motor was  not pushing Taleisin’s bow off like we
experienced with ducky on the quarter. It was actually easy to move her!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took Taleisin  out into the harbour  with her new motor, pushing  against a 2
knot current we were  making 4 knots over the ground.  Everything seemed to work
as  expected. It’s  worth noting  that Paul  had a  blast, we  both enjoyed  the
experience! Paul mentioned that we were busy making history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming  back into  the  berth was  not terribly  difficult  either, compared  to
previous experiences!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little premature  to call it a complete success. I still  need to see how
things behave  when under sail.  The interesting thing  I noticed is  that while
pushing along under  motor the bit of  timber used to brace  against the transom
actually  gets submerged  at times.  If the  motor did  not have  a 25”  shaft I
suspect it  would be  in danger  of drowning.  While I  don’t expect  any issues
there’s a chance that things might get interesting on a starboard tack. The only
way to find this out is to give it  a try. Given that the stern doesn’t go under
water when sailing  normally there’s no real  reason to believe the  motor is in
danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be  running with the motor  as is for the  time being so I  can figure out
what the next best  step would be. I’m currently thinking  that a tie-rod system
of some sort  would be a good  way to go. It’s  been pointed out to  me that the
taffrail might not be  as strong as it looks. For this I  might figure out a way
to get a block underneath it between the deck and the taffrail to strengthen it.
The other option I  am thinking about with regard to  strenthening the whole lot
is to replace the wire rigging underneath the bumpkin with a couple of tie-rods.
I wont  be making any decisions  in a hurry and  will test the system  in gentle
conditions first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next problem I’ll  be trying to solve, is a method for  lifting the motor on
board so  I can store  is down below  in the lazaret. If  I can devise  a simple
system for this it  would become possible to bring the motor  up on deck without
much drama  and most  of these  concerns might  go away.  Provided of  course it
becomes easy to do under way - which is probably far from trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like about this approach is that  I’ve not altered Taleisin, so if I want
to change anything I  can without consequences. I can fine  tune and evolve this
into more if I want  to or we can use it to learn  enough to become confident in
moving Taleisin the way she was intended  to be moved. We have more options with
this solution than  the alternatives, it’s not possible to  “unmake” holes. It’s
far from a perfect  solution, but it’s very pragmatic. It  looks like it belongs
on the boat too, which is a nice bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big  thank you  to everybody  who has  had any  discussions with  me regarding
motors and mounting them. It all added up and this is the sum total of all those
conversations, even  if you  suggested putting  a hole  in the  boat it  was all
valuable. We certainly would not have gotten  this far without all the input and
ideas from everybody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anybody reading this  sees a major flaw in my thinking,  please point it out!
If  you have  any  clever idea,  I’d  love to  hear  them! If  and  when I  make
significant changes I’ll do a follow up blog post if there’s any interest in it.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/training-wheels/&quot;&gt;Training Wheels&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on July 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Pick at It, You'll Only Make It Worse]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/dont-pick-at-it-youll-only-make-it-worse/" />
  <id>/dont-pick-at-it-youll-only-make-it-worse</id>
  <published>2016-07-11T14:00:27+12:00</published>
  <updated>2016-07-11T14:00:27+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Haul out day has arrived. When we  spent a day scrubbing Taleisin before we took
delivery of her, Annie told me that we’ll have to haul her out and sand her down
properly. As  always I should just  listen to Annie,  but that would be  far too
easy, it’s a much better idea to charge off and learn lessons the hard way…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While talking to my father on the phone I mentioned that I might buy him a plane
ticket from Australia to come and give me a hand - I was only kidding as I would
never put him to  work against his will. A couple of days  later my father calls
me up, asking when  Taleisin is coming out of the water as  he’s coming over and
give me a hand. Great I’ll have extra  hands to do more work. Annie’s father was
due in  New Zealand  shortly after and  he is  always keen to  lend a  hand with
anything  that  resembles  work.  There’s  a  lot  to  be  said  for  the  older
generation’s willingness to work, no matter  how soul destroying or miserable it
might be. So I started to make a list (oh how naive I was in my younger days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mum and dad arrived the day before haul out. Annie was away on school camp for a
few days so I was  holding down the fort - well as much  as can be expected when
people are foolish enough  to leave me in charge. In my  infinite wisdom I ended
up booking the  haul out during the  biggest classic boat regatta  in Auckland -
Taleisin should have been part of it.  Never mind, it’s booked people are coming
to  help so  I’m locked  in. We’ll  be back  in the  water before  long, 2  long
weekends should  be more  than enough  and with many  hands to  help it  will go
quick!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haul out was  much less adventurous than  I imagined it to be.  We simply walked
Taleisin  into the  cradle  and had  a  couple  of attempts  to  get her  seated
properly. I  probably drove the guys  in the boat  yard nuts as I  was concerned
at  every  step of  the  process.  Who wouldn’t  be,  a  boat like  Taleisin  in
irreplaceable. A big thank you to the crew  in the boat yard for putting up with
me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once Taleisin came out  of the water my parents thought I  was silly for wanting
to haul her and paint the hull,  “There’s nothing wrong with it, it looks good”.
Then  came  the mandatory  water  blasting,  again I  was  very  explicit in  my
instructions, keep  the lance far  away from the hull,  I don’t want  any damage
from water blasting! While the water  blasting process was taking place we could
see the anti fouling just flaking off. I’ll be the first to admit that I thought
we’d just be fairing in a few bits here and there and then painting over the top
to get her back in the water with a nice smooth bottom quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/24368144710/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1540&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c7.staticflickr.com/2/1700/24368144710_bdf0100f5b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1540&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went off to the store to get some supplies to get the sanding started. That’s
when  the first  signs of  woes to  come started  to appear.  Touching the  anti
fouling in some places caused it to  flake off, hosing it down with tap pressure
only did the same. Other areas it was &lt;strong&gt;stuck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had to hand sand as they only allowed wet sanding in the yard. It became soul
destroying very quickly and  there was no visible progress at  all. When you get
something that looks like  it might be faired in some paint  would flake off and
you start  again. Poking and  anything makes it  worse, sanding in  other places
makes it worse. This is soul destroying work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t  long before I realised  that we have to  go all the way  down to bare
teak. This was not  the plan! This job is much much  bigger than anticipated. So
much for the  list, now it’s just  a matter of getting this  one task completed.
Taleisin might only be twenty nine and a half feet long, but she’s a HUGE boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At  this  point  I  started  to  make  some phone  calls  to  see  how  much  it
might  cost to  get a  professional to  come  and do  the job,  most refused  to
touch  wooden  boats. There  was  only  one man  for  the  job, Alan  Boyd  from
&lt;a href=&quot;http://x-foul-e-8.com&quot;&gt;x-foul-e-8&lt;/a&gt;. The only problem was that Alan was busy and
couldn’t come and do  the job. Alan was kind enough to come  out to Taleisin and
provide very good advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After  Alan  advised  us on  how  to  proceed  we  had scrapers  to  remove  the
antifouling. Progress  was being made,  but it was  still really slow  going. We
scraped for 4 days, over the long weekend. Nobody in their right mind would find
this even remotely enjoyable. This is really  the dark side of boat ownership. I
believe it should be mandatory for any would be owner to clean the bottom of the
boat he intends to buy first, if you’re still wanting the boat after that you’re
good. It would  be interesting to see  how many people would still  go ahead and
buy the boat after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the scraping we still had to sand.  It was at this point that Annie talked
some sense into me and I realised that it  would be cheaper for me to be at work
while I paid someone else to finish the  job. It’s possible that one day I might
listen to her up front…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hard  part was  telling my  dad that I’m  getting someone  else to  come and
finish the job, my dad is one of those people who refuses to pay someone to do a
job he can do himself.  I felt guilty having put him to work  for 4 days of soul
destroying work only to get someone else to finish it up. Thanks Dad for all the
hard work, I really do appreciate it, I still feel bad for letting you work that
hard only to  end up getting someone else  to finish the job! In  my defence the
work was actually far from over, it would have taken us a long time to finish it
up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few phone calls back and forth  I finally managed to get a day that Alan
could come and do the work. Suffice to say  Alan made it look like it was a walk
in the park compared  to what we went through. The result  was awesome. This did
mean that  Taleisin was sitting  on the hard over  the second long  weekend with
nothing being  done too her. I  do believe everybody deserved  the break though,
the job was horrible and the pay was even worse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28152557901/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1545-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8585/28152557901_0c19fd747d_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1545-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28152555031/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1547-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7632/28152555031_be6cd97d92_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1547-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next  step was to get  painting done. Having  learnt my lesson on  the paint
removal part (also  I’ll admit reluctantly that Annie was  the sensible one, yet
again)… I enlisted  the help of professionals for this.  They promised me they
would start within a  day or 2 of Alan finishing his job.  This was important as
it was  during the  hottest part  of the  year (yes  lessons have  been learnt).
Taleisin was starting to dry out and she needed some paint on her bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally,  as with  anything  that involves  a boat,  things  take longer  than
expected. To those well  versed in the drill this will come  as no surprise, yet
somehow I’m surprised every time! The  company doing the painting couldn’t start
until the following week. While waiting on  the painting to start I noticed that
the seams are opening. This is not good news for a wooden boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/27949524180/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1548&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8848/27949524180_63ceebde7a_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1548&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I stopped reading online forums, every man and his dog was 
reporting on my progress on the forums 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://forums.sailinganarchy.com/index.php?showtopic=171298&amp;amp;hl=taleisin&amp;amp;page=2&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; 
and &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.woodenboat.com/showthread.php?171680-The-Pardeys-are-selling-Taleisin/page2&amp;amp;highlight=Taleisin&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
I hit a bit of a panic and of course knowing that the internet is watching I 
figured I had to do something and quick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled out  my phone and started with  A in my phone book.  I called everybody
that I thought might be able and willing  to help. I called Annie and told her I
was going to bucket  salt water onto the hull to get her  wet again. By the time
Annie arrived (50 minutes or so later) she saw this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/45nt5SM7dj0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this was quite an unexpected  evening for most of my friends and family,
it was a great relief to have such wonderful friends and family! Most people had
a lot of  fun, sure it was  hard work. It’s not  everyday you get to  be part of
something this  crazy though  (and when  I do  crazy, it’s  usually on  a fairly
decent scale)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bucket brigade was a huge success, albeit a little redundant. The next day I
drove all  over Auckland talking  and meeting with  boat builders. It  turns out
that since Taleisin  has been in the water  for so long, a hose  would have done
the trick just fine as there’s plenty of  salt in the wood. The boat builder had
a chuckle and said, “don’t lose any sleep over it”. Lessons learnt, but when you
hit a panic you solve a problem with the tools you have at your disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A very special thank you to everybody that answered the call that night, it is
very much appreciated!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some panic, running around, getting advice, hiding, and other shenanigans.
I finally  get around to  doing what I  should have done  in the first  place. I
bought  a lot  of shade  cloth and  hung it  around Taleisin.  This made  a huge
difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about  3 weeks on  the hard the painting  finally got underway.  After the
primer went on I breathed a sigh of relief! The guys painting Taleisin was great
and got  a coat of  paint on before  the 3 weekend  started, this made  me sleep
quite  a  bit better.  As  with  the  guys in  the  boat  yard, these  guys  had
to  put  up with  a  lot  from  me.  A big  thank  you  to  the team  at  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.glossboats.co.nz&quot;&gt;Gloss
boats&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/27949514230/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1559-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8677/27949514230_bbe7d71275_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1559-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next it was  a coat of blue anti foul.  The theory is that when we  start to see
blue on the hull  Taleisin is due for a few coats of  paint rather than just one
coat annually. Time will tell if this is a sound theory or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/27949512700/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1561-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8687/27949512700_7e0d8f23bd_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1561-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally this is followed by two coats in her natural colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28230177665/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1567-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8777/28230177665_e39c9c6270_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1567-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the  painting was  completed there  was one more  challenge, a  huge storm
rolled in. This was a pretty nasty one and a few boats ended on the rocks in the
mooring area where we keep Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28230176065/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1569&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8839/28230176065_b68362214d_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1569&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The storm delayed  us getting back in the  water, which was fine with  me. I was
actually happier with  Taleisin on the hard  than in the water.  After the storm
ran it’s course I was very sad to see that the little boat above was Patricia, a
carvel plank  H28. She went  back in the  water just as  we came out.  Her owner
spent a very long time fixing her up to get back in the water. I remember having
some banter  with him regarding engines.  He had to haul  Patricia again because
there was a leak around the prop shaft - I was a little smug about the fact that
Taleisin doesn’t have those kinds of issues.  I was heart broken when I saw this
though:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/27614521804/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1576-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7499/27614521804_fb3dc51a0b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1576-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After what can only be described as a nightmare of 4 weeks long, we were finally
getting the old girl back in the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28230173915/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1572-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8575/28230173915_c8a367ef2b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1572-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting  Taleisin  back on  the  mooring  was  rather  uneventful or  free  from
adventure if you wish…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days after I had finally got the  nerve to give Lin a call, I told her the
story. Lin had a chuckle and said: “Taleisin is a tough old boat”, what I should
have done was given Lin a call from the start and save myself a lot of worrying.
It’s how ever  very easy to be  reasonable after the fact, hind  sight is always
20/20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s taken me quite a while to write  about this ordeal, it’s not always easy to
face up to your short comings and admit that things weren’t always perfect. This
story  did have  a happy  ending, but  I can  assure you  that it  was a  fairly
stressful time for me. I have to admit  that the internet was rather kind to me,
it could have been so much worse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to  everybody who stopped by  an offered support and thank  you to all
those  who got  roped into  helping  with something  at some  point during  this
adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dont-pick-at-it-youll-only-make-it-worse/&quot;&gt;Don&#39;t Pick at It, You&#39;ll Only Make It Worse&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on July 11, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guest Blog  Post at  the Unlikely  Boat Builder]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/guest-blog-post-at-the-unlikely-boat-builder/" />
  <id>/guest-blog-post-at-the-unlikely-boat-builder</id>
  <published>2016-04-29T12:57:58+12:00</published>
  <updated>2016-04-29T12:57:58+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I’ve written a post. I’ve been quite snowed under with a
lot of different projects and my mind was refusing to co-operate. I was asked by
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unlikelyboatbuilder.com/&quot;&gt;John Almberg&lt;/a&gt;  to write  a guest  post for
his blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably of interest to everybody who’s following us. I wrote about why we&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;bought Taleisin. You can read the post &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unlikelyboatbuilder.com/2016/04/why-did-you-buy-taleisin.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/guest-blog-post-at-the-unlikely-boat-builder/&quot;&gt;Guest Blog  Post at  the Unlikely  Boat Builder&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on April 29, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Defeated in the Marina]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/defeated-in-the-marina/" />
  <id>/defeated-in-the-marina</id>
  <published>2016-01-22T20:56:04+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-22T20:56:04+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been  contemplating posting this story  for some time, clearly  this is not
one of  my finest  moments. I’ve  decided to  share it  because other’s  find it
pentertaining, and it might be a cautionary tale to would be engineless sailors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is normal for me, when I get a new  toy I want to use it. At this point we’ve
owned Taleisin  for a few weeks.  I’ve been out on  her once with Chad  from the
CYA. He  showed me how to  barge using Cheeky and  the 2.5hp motor, and  he also
taught  me how  to scull.  Chad  is super  experienced,  I didn’t  do the  whole
procedure myself and I don’t have any “what if” plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came up with a plan, if 2.5hp can do it, I can get an inflatable with a bigger
engine and that should  make things much easier. So I go shopping,  I get a 2.6m
Zodiac and an  8hp outboard. Armed with a  new sure fire way to  get Taleisin in
and out of  the marina I study the  weather forecasts and pick a  day that seems
like it would be perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get  up early on Saturday  morning, I’m very excited  - like a little  kid on
christmas morning. When  I’m excited about things,  I don’t hide it  very well -
everybody knows. Annie mentioned to me in the  car on the way to the marina that
she can tell that it’s one of those excited days for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we’re onboard at the marina I  start putting the inflatable together (I now
seem to  call her Ducky).  I attached  some lines to  Ducky, dropped her  in the
water and started to  tie her to the quarter. Keep in mind  this was pretty much
winter time  in New  Zealand so  I was  wearing foul  weather gear  and thermals
underneath them. It’s taken quite a bit longer to set everything up, which I now
know is normal for everything boat related. Eventually we get Taleisin ready for
sailing and start to go over “the plan”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the plan, Annie asks? We drop the mooring lines, I put the outboard in
reverse. We back out slowly, use Taleisin’s  rudder to steer and then get out of
here. Lets just give  it a go. That’s fine, Annie said, but  the wind has picked
up a bit…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be fine, I said…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We dropped the mooring  lines, I put the outboard in  reverse and Taleisin backs
out slowly. All  is going great so  far. Watch out behind you,  said Annie, that
boat is getting closer. I look behind me. I put the outboard in forward. We move
forward. Move the  tiller to the other  side we need to turn.  It’s not working,
says Annie. The wind was blowing the bow  off. We’re going to hit in front Annie
yells. Back in reverse. We do this a  few times. While we’re doing this the wind
is blowing  us sideways down  the channel.  “Take the dingy  and go push  on the
bow”, yells a spectator. What he didn’t know  is that I made a fatal mistake and
secured the dinghy a bit too well and there  was no way I would be able to untie
it in time. This was completely and utterly stupid of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided  to just  gun the outboard.  We need to  pick up  way so we  can turn.
That’s what the  problem is. We’re still  not turning. Back in  reverse, gun it!
Whoops that  boat behind  me is  getting close. I  hit a  piling with  the stern
anchor - I’ve bent  it slightly but it will survive. At this  point I think that
it might  be a  good idea to  go forward.  By now  the bow is  in a  much better
position  and we  might actually  get out.  I reach  for the  gear lever  on the
outboard and flick it to forward…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I say we’ll be fine? I was wrong…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except for the fact that I didn’t close the throttle while almost at full speed.
Big mistake. Rookie Mistake. The dingy still  tied to the quarter lifts it’s bow
out of the water and stands up right, I  try to hang onto the seat. No luck. The
outboard gets drowned. I end up in  the water. Taleisin is still heading for the
boats in front  of her. Annie thinking  quickly and with a bit  of guidance from
the audience we’ve now assembled on the dock, sprints up the bowsprit, grabs the
forestay, both feet up against the boat in front of us. She fends like a champ!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No crash  yet, that’s  good right.  While all of  this is  happening I’m  in the
water. Thinking to myself “oh crap, I have  to get back on board because this is
going south fast”. Hanging off the side  of Taleisin I quickly drag myself up to
the bow so I can get up on the bobstay to climb back on board. Another spectator
on the dock yells, get your motor going! I hop in Ducky, try to get her started,
no luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I get  back on board I see one of our  neighbors motoring out to come
and rescue us. “Throw  me a line”, he yells! “I’ll tow you  into the channel, no
worries mate”! I declined and opted to go back to the slip. “I killed the motor,
no idea how I’ll get back”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as we’re pulling  into the slip the marina boat shows up.  I quietly say to
Annie, I’m  in a  lot of trouble  now, they wont  be happy  about this. I  had a
sheepish  look  on my  face  and  was very  apologetic  about  the whole  thing.
Everybody just smiled and said “that’s boating, it won’t be your last…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I’m feeling pretty well  defeated. I’ve been defeated in the past,
but  NEVER like  this. Usually  there’s  some upside  to  the defeat  for me.  I
honestly could not  find an upside, nothing  went well. I did a  bunch of really
dumb  things,  and I  couldn’t  even  try to  deny  it.  The results  spoke  for
themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The marina boat  crew and our rescue crew  just had a chuckle and  were on their
way. We did give our rescuer a pack of beers as a thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outboard seemed to be fine when I got  it home and started it, I had a small
win. I was moping around for a few  days not quite knowing how to deal with this
defeat. My  tail was  firmly tucked  between my  legs. I  started reading  up on
warping techniques and  other engineless maneuvers. It took me  a while to build
up the courage to  take Taleisin out again. I did have  a perfect excuse though,
winter was in full swing and the weather was pretty nasty. My research paid off,
eventually,  we moved  Taleisin  to her  mooring  on our  own  without too  much
trouble. I  should probably listen to  Annie more, but my  stubbornness seems to
get the better of me at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please feel  free to  leave a comment  with your own  experiences. I  think I’ve
recovered from the trauma inflicted upon my  ego, you’re allowed to have a laugh
at my expense. Looking forward to hearing from anybody who reads this.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/defeated-in-the-marina/&quot;&gt;Defeated in the Marina&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 22, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ditching Work to Go Sailing...]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/ditching-work-to-go-sailing/" />
  <id>/ditching-work-to-go-sailing</id>
  <published>2016-01-20T16:24:28+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-20T16:24:28+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;So you wake up in the morning, it’s  perfect weather, the wind is just enough to
move  the boat  at a  slow  pace. You  think  to yourself,  “excellent, lets  to
sailing”. Suddenly you realise it’s Tuesday morning and you’re supposed to be at
work for meetings. So you make a decision….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did attend the required meetings and  told everybody in the office, that’s it,
I’m going sailing  see you tomorrow! I  went home, had a quick  lunch and loaded
Ducky in the car. Annie and I were off to the dock…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very  fortunate that I can  at times have flexibility  around working hours,
most of the time  we’re very busy and I have to keep  my nose to the grindstone.
I’m working towards freeing more time up  for playing. Annie is a school teacher
and she’s fortunately still on holiday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re becoming  more efficient at getting  away from the dock.  We were motoring
towards Taleisin in  Ducky in no time  at all. Once onboard Taleisin  we got her
prepped for  sailing, we looked  at each  other. We each  took a deep  breath. I
hoisted the main sail. We cast off the mooring line. Taleisin fell off the wind.
The main sail filled and we were sailing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/24141559759/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1517&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1467/24141559759_ca80f35045_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1517&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we  built up a little  way Annie hoisted the  stays’l, I sheeted it  in and
Taleisin was moving well.  We only set the stays’l since we  just wanted to sail
at  a snails  pace and  enjoy  the water.  We were  not  going fast  but it  was
glorious!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23881140514/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1518&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1660/23881140514_16466c906b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1518&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we were moving  slowly and just kicking back Annie went  down below to get
her fishing rod.  She sat on the  cabin top happily trawling  while we’re moving
slowly through  the water. I  could tell by  the look on  her face that  she was
quite content. I should point out that she was fishing and directing me where to
go etc…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23881375394/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1520&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1576/23881375394_afa50b1157_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1520&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While  Annie was  trying to  catch dinner  I was  happily sailing  the boat  and
tacking back  and forth on my  own. I’m sure it  was less than impressive  but I
wanted to experiment  and it was fun  and non threatening. It felt  like a great
opportunity to  do some  learning. We didn’t  spend a huge  amount of  time out,
maybe an hour or two. Then is was time to head back to the mooring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23882532203/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1522&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1476/23882532203_c1fd3dc935_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1522&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23881134184/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1521&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1506/23881134184_eb69c94f35_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1521&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we got closer to the mooring field  we decided to drop the stays’l and sail
in under  the main  only. In  theory that sounded  like it  would work,  but the
current was stronger than our drive under  main only. Realising the error in our
ways we  had the stays’l up  again and made our  way into the mooring  field. We
dropped the stays’l again and attempted  to approach the mooring from down wind.
Things didn’t work out that well. Annie said, umm that boat behind us is getting
closer. The boat was not moving, we were going backwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran forward hoisted the stays’l, yelled  “sheet it in”! Taleisin picked up way
again and Annie was  able to steer us clear of the  few surrounding boats. While
she was doing this I moved quickly and maybe in a slight panic to get Ducky tied
on the quarter and get the engine running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the engine started  to push Taleisin I dropped the  sails. Annie said, “The
boats not turning the right way”! Due to the fact that the engine is pushing her
in the other direction. I responded, “then  turn the other way”! Annie moved the
tiller, Taleisin  responded and  we steered  well clear of  all other  boats. In
reality we were never  anywhere near any of these boats  they were actually well
clear of us - it just felt like  they were getting closer. We probably had a few
boat lengths between us at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great, now  we have  control of  the situation! “Where’s  the mooring  buoy?”, I
asked. Annie  pointed it  out and  we slowly pushed  Taleisin towards  it. While
doing this is  became obvious that the wind  wants to blow the bow  off and just
using the tiller  alone was not going  to do the trick.  I started experimenting
and learning again. I found that if I moved the outboard tiller all the way over
I can  use it like  a stern thruster  and quickly point  the bow in  a different
direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tried to get to the mooring buoy,  no luck, the current keeps pushing us off.
“Approach it so the current pushes you onto the mooring”, says Annie, “Like I’ve
already told you to do”. So we gave that a try, it worked, easily. I grabbed the
buoy and tied a line to it so I  could in theory relax and deal with things in a
calm manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nice idea, I still  felt the need to haul the mooring line  over the bow roller,
tied another  line through the  attachment loop and  secured it around  a winch.
“Let’s get  this thing secured”,  after a  bit of effort  we managed to  get the
mooring attached securely. I turned to Annie and gave her a high five, “success,
we did it”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will  confess that  my adrenaline  spiked and I  was less  than cool  calm and
collected. Annie was a champ, she never missed  a beat! I needed to sit down and
collect myself. I  also had the greatest  feeling of accomplishment as  I sat on
the foredeck! Who  knew that something this simple can  feel this satisfying! Is
this what is meant by enjoying the simpler things in life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tidied Taleisin up, Annie put some salt water on the deck. We loaded Ducky up
and went  back to the dock.  Once we were tied  up I remember thinking,  “Wow, I
didn’t loose anything overboard”.  That was a bad thought. Just  as I lifted the
outboard from Ducky I noticed the trim rod  was lose and hanging out. I tried to
put the motor down to get it and at the moment it fell out and I watched it sink
in the water.  This is just ridiculous!  At this rate I’ll have  nothing left to
lose soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We  went home,  content with  yet another  adventure provided  by Taleisin,  she
surely is turning out to be an adventure machine.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ditching-work-to-go-sailing/&quot;&gt;Ditching Work to Go Sailing...&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 20, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sailing in Cheeky]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/sailing-in-cheeky/" />
  <id>/sailing-in-cheeky</id>
  <published>2016-01-18T21:33:12+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-18T21:33:12+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;“Let’s go sailing in the dinghy” was  the words that Annie uttered on a Saturday
morning. The  weather was wonderful  and there  was not a  lot of wind.  She was
excited about the prospect  of sailing in the dinghy. I  was thinking to myself,
this is huge, Annie is pushing &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; to  go sailing. So we loaded the car up with
Cheeky’s oars and small 2.5hp outboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting  cheeky launched  was quick  and easy  and  we were  on our  way out  to
Taleisin in no time. You might be wondering why we’re going to Taleisin if we’re
dinghy sailing!?  The answer is simple,  of course, Cheeky’s mast,  rudder, drop
board, tiller and sail  is onboard Taleisin. Once we got  to Taleisin we grabbed
everything we needed to rig cheeky for sailing  and went back to the dock to rig
her up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we got back to  the dock I spent a bit of time trying  to figure out how to
make this little boat  sail. Granted I don’t know much  about boats and sailing,
it didn’t take much to figure out a way to get the pieces to fit so it can sail.
I was quite surprised at the simplicity. Lin  once said to me that a sailboat is
an  incredibly simple  machine, and  I  guess you  can be  excused for  thinking
otherwise looking at modern yachts loaded to the gunwales with complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So having the boat rigged up and ready to attempt to sail her I went back to the
car to store  the outboard motor. I returned  to the dock and we cast  off to go
sailing. We had  a slight problem, no  wind. Don’t worry, Annie  said look there
are boats sailing out there, pointing to the harbor, lets just row out for a bit
until we can catch  a breeze. So Annie being the champ that  she is, grabbed the
oars and started to  row us out! It didn’t take long before  the sail filled and
we started sailing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were  moving slowly, but we  were moving. It  was very nice and  relaxing, we
went out into the channel of the harbor, tacked back and forth for about an hour
and then we decided to head back for lunch. We slowly sailed through the mooring
field and back to  the dock. Annie asked if we should row  back to the dock, but
me being as stubborn as a mule wanted to sail back. Slowly but surely we made it
back to the  dock and gently docked  Cheeky under sail. It was  a small victory,
but we  did dock under sail.  It certainly is  nothing like it would  be docking
Taleisin, but it was an achievement none the less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos weren’t high priority for us, here’s a couple of bad “selfies”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23864001004/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1514&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1489/23864001004_e58fabac29_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1514&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/24196634050/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1516&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1444/24196634050_998d234e74_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1516&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safely back at the  dock we started to disassemble cheeky and  moved her back to
the dinghy rack. Where’s  the car keys, I asked Annie?  We looked everywhere for
the keys. We couldn’t find the car keys!  I asked around to see if anybody would
know where they might get handed in if anybody found them. I eventually get hold
of  the on  site security  guard.  She was  a  lovely lady,  very friendly,  and
helpful.  After a  bit  of looking  around and  digging  through everything  the
security guard asked if she could call us  a tow truck to come and open the car,
at  this point  I thought  I may  have locked  them in  the car  when I  put the
outboard away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the tow  truck underway and me cursing  under my breath as to  how stupid I
am, I ran into the crew from Pinch  of Salt. I enquired as to the whereabouts of
their  dinghy. Apparently  they  have located  it on  TradeMe  (the New  Zealand
version of E-Bay) and was trying to figure out how to get it back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tow truck arrives,  the driver takes 3 seconds to open the  door. No keys in
the car, bugger! We paid the driver  the $80 fee for his services. What happened
next was unexpected and a nice surprise.  The driver offered to drive us home to
get our spare key for the car. We quickly loaded everything into the car, locked
it up and accepted the kind offer with a smile!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we arrived home we had another challenge! The key to the house was attached
to the key for the car. We’re in luck we have a locksmith around the corner from
us,  a very  friendly guy  and  also a  sailor  (well this  is Auckland,  almost
everybody is a sailor).  I wondered over to see if he  was home. Slight problem,
he was out fishing for the day, but his lovely wife suggested that their 18 year
old son  bring the  ladder around  and climb  through the  window we  left open.
Success! We got inside, got the spare key and went back to the dock in our other
car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our way  back to the dock Annie  suggested that we stop and get  a cold drink
and ice-cream for  the security guard that  was so helpful and  friendly. It was
nice to  put a smile on  her face and she  really appreciated it as  the sun was
beating down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So naturally  after we  got home,  I posted  a little  about this  experience on
cruisers forum. One  of the members pointed  out that it might  pay to sacrifice
some coins  upfront to the  ocean as  it would appear  that I’m paying  for safe
passage one way or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great time, and it was another adventure thanks to Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sailing-in-cheeky/&quot;&gt;Sailing in Cheeky&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 18, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mooring Under Sail]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/mooring-under-sail/" />
  <id>/mooring-under-sail</id>
  <published>2016-01-06T16:40:39+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-06T16:40:39+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;We got  up early today  to go sailing  on Taleisin! We  loaded the car  with our
inflatable  training wheels  and made  our  way to  the dock.  We started  going
through the motions of assembling the ducky to transport us out to Taleisin. The
reason we  had to get up  early was to make  our way out to  Taleisin to collect
another life jacket. The extra life jacket  was for Bud, a classic sail maker in
Auckland from  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.naldersails.com&quot;&gt;Nalder sails&lt;/a&gt;.  I’ve been  told that
Bud is  an expert  in the field  of classic  sail making, he’s  an old  salt and
absolutely loves the classics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On board Taleisin  we started to get  her ready to go sailing,  undoing the sail
covers, running the sheets, putting the tiller in place, the usual things you do
before you go sailing. Bud called to tell me he’s running a little late. We were
fine with that  as we were just hanging  out on Taleisin and it was  a nice day.
Unfortunately for us Taleisin is moored in a spot where the sea state is exactly
right to induce motion  sickness. Annie had already taken sea  legs and was just
chilling out on the  foredeck, I on the other hand, had not  and started to feel
the effects of sea sickness setting. This  was mostly due to me playing with the
y-valve in the  galley for the drain.  Rookie mistake, I know.  The smell coming
out of  it was  something awful  and made  my stomach  churn. Luckily  I’ve been
reading about this stuff and decided to get up on deck quickly. After some fresh
air I went down below looking for sea legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll have to use your imagination as I didn’t take any photos, but there I was
laying  down in  the cockpit  trying to  regain my  composure. At  this point  I
thought it  might be best if  I headed back to  the dock to gain  some stability
back! I left  Annie on board Taleisin,  grabbed an extra life  jacket, jumped in
the ducky and went back to the dock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting at  the dock things  were getting much better  quickly and I  forgot all
about  that nasty  y-valve incident.  While waiting  a couple  of young  sailors
walked up and  asked me if the dinghy  tied to the dock belonged to  me. After a
bit of conversation they explained how they went out for a sail the previous day
and the  tow rope on their  dinghy sheared through.  The offered to pay  me some
money to  ferry them  to their  boat. I  politely declined  the offer  for money
(seemed like it  would be bad karma  to accept money for  something this simple)
and suggested that  if they just hang  around till Bud arrives  that I’ll gladly
drop them  off on  their yacht,  Pinch of  Salt. I  do have  to give  these guys
credit, they were about to swim out  to their yacht with all their provisions on
a float. They would how ever have to swim back to the dock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bud arrived, all for of us piled into  Ducky with all the provisions too. Off we
went! The crew  of Pinch of Salt was  happy once aboard and we  continued on our
way to Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once on board Taleisin  we hanked on the jib. Bud asked me  if I wanted to leave
under sail instead of  hip towing. My answer was “of  course”! Bud explained the
procedure and what he expected Taleisin  to do while we’re doing this. Basically
Taleisin is so sea  kindly and well balanced that we hoisted  the main, cast the
mooring line off and  she just fell off the wind and we  were sailing under main
only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we got outside  the mooring field we hoisted the stays’l  and she picked up
speed. The  jib on Taleisin is  on a separate  stay from the forestay,  this was
done so that Lin  and Larry could deal with the jib without  having to go out on
the bowsprit while  rounding Cape Horn. We didn’t tighten  this properly because
the mooring line  was over the rope gypsy  while we were moored. I  was having a
bit of fun  and games up on the bow  trying to sort this out while  under way. I
can say this, I’m very glad that Larry put 8 inch bulwarks all around Taleisin’s
deck, it certainly made life a LOT easier  on the bow. To add insult to injury I
didn’t sort  the down haul for  the jib out properly  so I was running  back and
forth trying to  hoist the jib. After  screwing around for probably  a good 5-10
minutes with this I finally managed to get the jib up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went  back to the  cockpit, we sheeted  the jib in,  put Taleisin hard  on the
wind. It was glorious! It’s the first time we’ve had Taleisin under full sail! I
had the biggest grin on my face and so did Bud - not sure which of us was having
more fun! Annie was  hanging out in the companion way for  most of the duration,
only jumping out to help with sheets when we were tacking of gybing. While Annie
is no stranger to adventure and extreme sports, she’s a much better rock climber
than I am,  she’s not comfortable on  the water at all. She  should be commended
for agreeing  to buy  Taleisin and to  sail with me,  she is  absolutely amazing
because she  will push  herself well out  of her comfort  zone and  perform much
better than I ever could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After tacking back and forth up wind Bud suggested we gybe and come up alongside
one of the old New Zealand America’s cup yachts. That was a bit of fun, but they
left us behind rather quickly! Bud showed me how to get Taleisin to run downwind
wing and wing. This will take some practice to do confidently!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we knew it  we were back at the mooring field and  Bud was explaining how
to come in under  sail. Bud made this look super easy! We  rounded up slowly and
ghosted onto the mooring buoy, I grabbed it  with the boat hook and then the fun
started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was quite a bit more load on  the line than expected, I couldn’t just hold
Taleisin in place, Annie came up to the  bow and asked if she could help. I said
get me a line so I can tie this damn thing off. Looking back I should have taken
a turn on something with the line and it would have been a lot less exciting! We
got it  tied off. I put  a line through the  bow roller and around  the windlass
rope gypsy. Bud and myself heaved the mooring  line up and we managed to tie the
line through  the mooring  line’s loop.  We ended  up winching  the rest  in and
eventually got the  mooring line secured. This was probably  the hardest part of
the whole experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With  all of  that  done we  tidied  Taleisin up  and  we spent  a  bit of  time
discussing  Taleisin’s new  sails. I  think  it’s safe  to say  that we’re  very
excited about  the new sails, they  should look absolutely awesome  and Taleisin
will have more  of a classic look with  them than she does now. This  might be a
bit counter to what  Lin and Larry would have done, but I  don’t think they will
mind too much, it’s all about making the old girl look really good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dinghy ride back was not quite as good. I’m a pretty average dinghy helmsman
and got the  entire crew wet in the chop.  In spite of all of this  Bud was kind
enough to  agree to mentor  us on how  to do things under  sail! This is  a huge
relief as doing things without an engine and learning that way is quite tough on
your own when you’re not entirely sure what you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming months  Bud will produce new sails for Taleisin,  we’ll be sure to
take some pictures of her with the new sails…&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mooring-under-sail/&quot;&gt;Mooring Under Sail&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 06, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Windlass spring]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/windlass-spring/" />
  <id>/windlass-spring</id>
  <published>2016-01-04T14:33:36+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-04T14:33:36+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This might seem like a strange post. In fact it is. I was contacted by John, who
needed to  know the dimensions  of a  particular spring in  Taleisin’s Windlass.
He’s got the same Windlass and the spring  is in pieces. I figured that I’d post
this as it just might come in handy for someone else in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up, here’s the plastic pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23792203469/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1474&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1441/23792203469_cc43ed49e2_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;516&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1474&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve read the strength of a spring is determined by:&lt;br /&gt;
1. Wire diameter&lt;br /&gt;
2. Outer diameter&lt;br /&gt;
3. Free Length (length of spring)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
4. Number of total coils&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wire diameter: 0.7 mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23531821304/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1478&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1693/23531821304_89d16574b9_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1478&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outer diameter: 5mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23531821304/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1478&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1693/23531821304_89d16574b9_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1478&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free length: 39.9mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/24160019885/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1476&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1600/24160019885_1f0264c0ce_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1476&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I counted 57 coils, also 39.9 / 0.7 = 57&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also measured the ends: 26.4mm (but this might be a little bit off as I didn’t
remove the screw).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23864397880/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1479&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1559/23864397880_8914e58bef_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1479&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a calculator that might be of use: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acxesspring.com/extension-spring-calculator-instructions.html&quot;&gt;Calculator - external link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimate of length inside “hooks” 92.360 mm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need more accuracy, let me know,  and I’ll take screws out and measure it
correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/windlass-spring/&quot;&gt;Windlass spring&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving Day...]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/moving-day/" />
  <id>/moving-day</id>
  <published>2015-10-29T20:56:22+13:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-29T20:56:22+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;We woke  up in the  morning, I said  to Annie “if  we’re going to  move Taleisin
today, we better get going. Not much wind  but it will pick up later today”. You
might  wonder, move  Taleisin where?  Taleisin has  been sitting  snugly in  the
marina all winter, as you might imagine  getting an 8 ton engineless boat out of
a marina can be a little challenging. We have recently had a new mooring laid in
a spot that’s easy to sail on and off. This is where Taleisin is moving to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve had some previous attempts at getting  out of the marina, one didn’t go to
well and the other  turned into a warping practice run. I  might write about the
first attempt one day  but the bruises are still visible on my  ego. In short, I
ended up in the water and I drowned an outboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in  preparation for our adventure,  we prepared Taleisin for  sailing, talked
through our plan, had  a disagreement, came to an agreement  and we were finally
ready to  give it a  “go”. We did  all of this in  just 2 hours.  Given previous
experience I’d be lying if I said that  I wasn’t nervous, but I had to hide this
from Annie as it would make her more nervous, she was already not that confident
in my ability  to pull this little stunt  off. Not being one to shy  away from a
challenge, I just  dragged my feet for  a little bit building up  the courage to
give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have  asked me in the past  how we deal with the lack  of an engine,
here’s the current way of doing things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Warp out of the berth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strap the dingy to the quarter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;barge out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warp1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Getting ready to warp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the warp lines around the pilings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warp2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Getting ready to warp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pulled her out slowly using the mooring lines (not in the diagram).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warp3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Getting ready to warp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annie was in  the cockpit pulling on the  stern line to turn the boat.  I was on
the bow pulling the boat closer to avoid the bow sprit hitting the pilings. This
was something that happened the first time we tried to warp out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warp4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Getting ready to warp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that the direction the boat is pointing in is the direction of
the channel. We tied the dingy to the hip and barged out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s worth noting  a few things that we learned from  this. Firstly we warped
her  out really  well, it  felt great!  However,  do not  put the  dingy on  the
opposite side of the  pilings. While there’s no way on, the  dingy will push the
boat  into  the  pilings (there  was  no  wind  to  push us  off  the  pilings).
Consequently we had a lot of fending to do, this is hard work if you’re moving a
heavy boat.  Once you have  way on (and Taleisin  doesn’t need much),  it’s very
easy to  move the boat  in this manner!  The original plan  was to push  off the
pilings and drift into the middle of the channel, unfortunately this didn’t work
out. Next time I’d get the dingy between the boat the and pilings (still need to
figure out how we’d go about this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few gut busting  seconds later Taleisin was moving fast  enough for the rudder
to be effective! I  looked at Annie raised a fist in the  air and said, the hard
part  is over!  Annie obviously  didn’t  share my  victory  as we  still had  to
navigate our way out of the marina and into the harbour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally making it out  of the marina, Annie commented how she’s  very glad to be
out of the marina as it’s  been nothing but unpleasant boating experience inside
it. I can completely understand her point of view as it’s been super challenging
and we kept getting beaten down by Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next  challenge was to hoist  the sails, luckily  we picked a day  with very
little wind.  Annie went forward  and hoisted the main,  it didn’t seem  to move
us… The  next minute a  powerboat came speeding by  at what was  definitely in
excess of 12 knots (harbour limits). The wake nearly tipped the dingy and almost
drowned the outboard. I leapt over the life  lines and onto the dingy to keep it
upright. We traveled  under motor a little  bit longer but the  power boats were
traveling way too fast and it felt like  we were inside a washing machine. I cut
the outboard and let the dingy trail  behind. I hoisted the staysail and went to
sit in the cockpit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ghetto sounder/chart plotter indicated that  we were traveling at 1-2 knots.
Since it didn’t really  feel like we had much in the way  of steerage I can only
assume that  the current  was pushing us  along. It was  interesting to  see how
quickly Annie’s dislike for power boats grew as we were drifting, she’s a proper
sailor now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After drifting for a while and getting thrown around by power boat wakes for too
long Annie persuaded me  to put the dingy back on the  quarter and push Taleisin
towards the mooring. Once I got the  dingy pushing along we actually saw 5 knots
on the Dragonfly pro,  I’m guessing at least 1-2 of  those were current related.
It’s worth noting that the outboard was  only at half throttle and only 8HP. Now
that we were moving we were making great  progress, I also didn’t have to sit in
the dingy the whole way and could just steer with the rudder on Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approaching the mooring I hopped into the dingy and slowed the engine down, when
we got close enough I just let the engine idle and we kept moving slowly towards
the buoy.  Pickup was a  breeze. There  was only one  problem, this was  not our
mooring. Since it’s a new mooring and we’ve never used it we didn’t know what to
look for. But the mooring number was not the number I was given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So rather  than panic  I got  the engine  pushing along  slowly again  and Annie
steered  us towards  another buoy.  We followed  the same  recipe as  before and
pickup was very  easy again! We secured  Taleisin to the mooring and  had a high
five moment!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if  you’re reading  along and thinking  that’s the end  of the  adventure you
would be forgiven since  for most it probably would be. We’re  not most and this
is when we got seasick for no apparent reason. Taleisin was rolling quite a bit,
we still can’t figure out why. I was telling myself to just push through and get
everything stashed  away and tidied  up. Annie lay down  on the foredeck  and it
looked like a good idea to me. We  spent about an hour just laying there feeling
pretty horrible. I’d  get up from time to  time trying to keep on  working but I
didn’t have much luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually Annie felt well enough to get back  to work, when I got up to try and
help I got instructed to lay back down as I was apparently not looking the best.
Annie soldiered on like a champ and put Taleisin in order!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had  one task that  we needed to  do before we could  head for the  dock, get
cheeky&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; off her  chocks. I had a few attempts  at this and eventually
managed to get the  job done without going green completely!  Once this task was
done we loaded up the dingy with everything we needed to take back with us, then
we learnt something interesting….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon  as we got on  the dingy the seasickness  was gone. Since the  motion of
the  dingy  was  different to  the  motion  of  Taleisin  we felt  better,  next
time  I’m getting  in  the dingy!  Motoring  back  to the  dock  we were  towing
Cheeky&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;,  eventually getting  back to  the  dock the  packing up  and
loading the  car up  took a  while. Approximately  8 hours  after we  started we
finished by  stopping for lunch  on the  way back to  the marina to  collect our
mooring lines and other car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;par error:
Cannot justify.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/moving-day/&quot;&gt;Moving Day...&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on October 29, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ghetto Depth Sounder]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/ghetto-depth-sounder/" />
  <id>/ghetto-depth-sounder</id>
  <published>2015-10-24T21:52:43+13:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-24T21:52:43+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Learning to sail a  boat like Taleisin is challenging at  best, learning to sail
on a boat like Taleisin takes things up a notch! Training wheels! That’s what we
need!  While  Taleisin has  got  a  perfectly good  lead  line  on board  (still
functioning as well  as the day the  Pardeys installed it), we’ve  got plenty to
get right  without the worry  about how deep the  water is. Enter  the Raymarine
Dragonfly 4 Pro, now don’t get me  wrong, there’s no substitute for common sense
and we  fully intend  on moving to  old school navigation  and old  school depth
sounding. Baby steps are normally the way to start, jumping in the deep end with
a boat like Taleisin provides plenty  of challenge without the added bits around
the edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after spending  some time searching around  and scratching my head  I came up
with this little design. It’s a 25mm PVC  pipe with a 20mm dowel shoved down the
inside. It’s a prototype, the idea is  that the dowel prevents the flex, and PVC
is pretty well suited  to being in water. I still need to  seal the bottom of it
using some  silicon or epoxy or  what ever will do  the job. It should  be quite
obvious  to  the  observer that  we  don’t  intend  on  putting a  through  hull
transducer on  Taleisin and  that this  is just a  “portable” sounder  and chart
plotter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/22243349589/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1337&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/663/22243349589_36106320d1_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1337&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lashing the pipe to the transom as  a temporary measure, I will do this slightly
better before I take it out for a test sail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/22404136546/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1338&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5703/22404136546_d38cf9aa86_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;768&quot; height=&quot;1024&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1338&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fashioned  some form of  plug and  play system using  an existing 12V  plug in
Taleisin. We’re  not very keen  on altering  Taleisin without having  thought it
through properly. This allows me to play and if I choose to throw it out, nobody
will know any better (well maybe they will  if they read this post). I guess I’m
trying to say that the boat will not be harmed with this little experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/22242426758/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1341&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5785/22242426758_6bab8d10a8_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;768&quot; height=&quot;1024&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1341&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an added little bonus, it’s got  a GPS chart plotter for added entertainment.
This will provide  a makeshift set of instrumentation for  speed, depth and GPS.
While I could have  used an iPad - and I thought about  it, using some wifi type
transducer with the Navionics app. This would  have left me with the small issue
that it’s not waterproof. After doing a lot of reading I ended up going with the
dragonfly instead, added bonus is that I can connect the iPad via wifi and still
have a larger  screen. I also think I  might get better battery life  out of the
dragonfly than the iPad, but time will tell!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/22404132386/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1339&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5650/22404132386_e7530ce891_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1339&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How will all  of this work out?  I have no idea,  but if it works  it will allow
some training wheels  during the early stages.  Once we get up  to standard with
our skills it wont matter any more.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ghetto-depth-sounder/&quot;&gt;Ghetto Depth Sounder&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on October 24, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sailing Taleisin for the First Time]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/sailing-taleisin-for-the-first-time/" />
  <id>/sailing-taleisin-for-the-first-time</id>
  <updated>2015-10-24T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-10-22T22:15:33+13:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This story begins early the previous morning. We had to drive 1 hour to Sandspit
to catch the  ferry which would drop us  off on the Pardey’s jetty.  Once we got
there we  rowed out to Taleisin  like we have done  a few times in  the past. We
loaded our personal belongings onto Taleisin, only what we needed to survive for
the next 2 days. This meant we had some food and warm clothes should the weather
require it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After loading our personal belongings on the boat we spent some time with Lin in
the boat  workshop. She  spent quite a  while explaining what  all the  bits and
pieces are that we should be loading onto  Taleisin. There was a big pile of it,
I remember asking Lin where it would all  fit. Lin assured me that it’s all been
on Taleisin and that she will swallow it without any issues. After going through
everything in  detail we began the  long day of ferrying  everything to Taleisin
via Cheeky&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. I  had a discussion with Lin about  the weather forecast
as some heavy weather was forecast for  the afternoon. We decided that we’ll set
sail early  in the morning  and we should hopefully  beat the bad  weather, it’s
only about 30 nautical miles to sail. Loading Taleisin took a very long and time
we were absolutely exhausted as we finished the last load in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got  up as early  as we could  manage, had a  quick breakfast and  started to
prepare Taleisin  to set sail. I  rigged up a GoPro  and set it to  record while
this was going on.  Underestimating the battery life on the GoPro  it ran out of
power long before things got exciting. Below  is an edit of some of the footage,
there’s not much going on but it will give you an idea of what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yCuMyVlxJ3A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something to keep in mind, Annie and I  have never sailed a big boat on our own.
We’ve had some  sailing lessons, been on  a couple of sailing  trips with people
who are experienced. That was about the  extent of our sailing experience on big
boats. I’m  very fortunate  that my  day job  requires me  to learn  things very
quickly, retain them, and put them to use almost immediately. This skill came in
very handy when it was time to sail  Taleisin out of the cove. Taleisin does not
have an engine, this  means there’s a bonus challenge when  it comes to sailing,
everything must be done under sail or via sculling oar. Given that at this point
I’ve never sculled a boat in my life, we’re sailing off the mooring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It  was very  calm in  the morning  and hardly  any wind  in the  cove. Once  we
prepared Taleisin, I asked  Annie if she’d prefer to be on the  helm or drop the
mooring line. She opted  to drop the mooring line as  it was less responsibility
and something she felt was easier to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stored  cheeky&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; on deck, hoisted  the sails, tucked a  reef in the
main and Annie  went forward to drop  the mooring line. I pulled  the sheets in,
pulled the tiller over,  took a deep breath… thinking “here  we go”! The sails
filled gently  Taleisin picked  up enough  way and we  started moving.  I recall
Annie asking, so when  do we start sailing? My response  was, we’re sailing now,
it’s just very slow, but we’re sailing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We slowly weaved our way through all the moored boats and eventually made it out
of the  cove. We  decided the previous  night that we’d  sail through  the inner
channel as it seemed like it might be more sheltered in case the weather pick up
as there was a  few islands that might provide some  protection from the rougher
seas. We had a glorious morning of  easy sailing, the winds were light the water
was smooth. I remember thinking, this is  what life should be all about! Sailing
is slow  going, it’s  great if  you don’t  have to  be anywhere  in a  hurry! We
removed the reef from the main and hoisted the big jib instead of the staysail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we sailed  past Motuora Island things  started to get a  bit more exciting.
The wind has slowly increased and we  haven’t noticed as we’ve been running with
it the whole way. The waves started to  build. We don’t agree on the exact hight
of  the waves,  but they  were sufficiently  big enough  to cause  Annie to  get
seasick. The swell was  beam on, at no point did we feel  in danger so we didn’t
change course. Taleisin was just taking this all in her stride. Annie spent some
time  hanging over  the lee  rail.  She eventually  recovered and  we sailed  on
towards the Whagaparoa passage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point We  changed course towards long bay, the swell  was now pushing us
along and Taleisin  was surfing the waves -  this is a LOT of  fun. Taleisin was
very stable during  this whole experience! After  doing a bit of  fun sailing we
realised that  we should probably  sail around Devenport.  I went down  below to
grab the ipad to verify our position and  check out the charts on it. Due to the
sea state I rushed  back up on deck and I turned green  very quickly. Now it was
my turn to hang over the lee rail for over an hour. Annie did a fantastic job at
the helm while I recovered. At this point we’re sailing towards Rangitoto Island
with the intention of jibing once we pass Devenport. It will be an easy run into
the marina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we  got to Devenport  I said to  Annie, lets Jibe!  So we went  through the
procedure, started to jibe… That’s when I realised that the wind was blowing a
&lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; stronger than we  realised. All of a sudden the heel was  far more than we
were comfortable. I yelled let the sheets go!  Annie let the jib sheet go, I let
the main sheet go, I pulled the helm  hard over, Taleisin came back up right and
I pointed her  into the wind. I yelled  out to Annie, get on the  helm, keep her
into the wind, I’m changing sails and reefing the main.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went  forward, dropped  the jib,  dropped the main,  put a  reef in  the main,
hoisted the main and hoisted the staysail.  That felt much better, less sail was
a lot more manageable. Later we learned that the wind was 30kts gusting 35kts. I
took the tiller, let Taleisin drop off and we started to sail again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here  on out  the sailing was  actually pretty easy  going. While  about 30
minutes away  from the marina  I called  the marina up  asking the push  boat to
assist us getting into  our marina berth. I was advised to radio  once we get in
and they will come and tie up next to  us. When we got to the marina entrance we
rounded up into the wind, I dropped  the head sail, tucked another reef into the
main. This was when I had the most expensive accident for the day, the jib sheet
knocked my sun glasses off my head and  I watched them sink to the bottom of the
harbour  - I  had a  fleeting  thought about  jumping  in after  them, but  then
realised that it was probably a very bad idea. I yelled some expletives (see I’m
a real sailor now) and sailed into the marina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we entered the marina I got onto the radio and the marina boat met us about
half way down the channel. They tied up next to us and we dropped the main sail.
I made the mistake of thinking that the  push boat crew would know what they are
dealing with. Things  got really exciting as they didn’t  realise just how heavy
Taleisin is. We  had a few near  misses with other boats, but  eventually we got
Taleisin all tied up. We sat down for a couple of minutes to regain composure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went  down below, I grabbed  my phone and gave  Lin a call “Your  baby is all
tied up in Westhaven, all safe and sound”. I recanted some of the adventures and
I could sense  that she was relieved  that we made it without  anything major go
wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learnt more during  that one trip than we did during a  whole week’s worth of
sailing  lessons. We  had  to respond  quickly,  we  had to  think  on our  feet
(something  I’m fortunately  used to  due to  my day  job). More  importantly we
learnt that if things  go wrong get yourself into a position  where you can slow
down, think, regroup and solve the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be remiss  of me if I didn’t point out that  this story mostly reflects
the abilities of Taleisin and not that of  our own. I’m convinced that if it was
a lesser boat,  things would not have  been so smooth. We are  indeed very proud
care takers of this well found vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lin       Pardey       wrote       her       side       of       the       story
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.landlpardey.com/june-2015-newsletter.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sailing-taleisin-for-the-first-time/&quot;&gt;Sailing Taleisin for the First Time&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on October 22, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
