<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Taleisin - Adventure Machine!</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2016-07-11T15:30:33+12:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Eben and Annie</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Pick at It, You'll Only Make It Worse]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/dont-pick-at-it-youll-only-make-it-worse/" />
  <id>/dont-pick-at-it-youll-only-make-it-worse</id>
  <published>2016-07-11T14:00:27+12:00</published>
  <updated>2016-07-11T14:00:27+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Haul out day has arrived. When we spent a day scrubbing Taleisin before we took delivery of her, Annie told me that we’ll have to haul her out and sand her down properly. As always I should just listen to Annie, but that would be far too easy, it’s a much better idea to charge off and learn lessons the hard way…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While talking to my father on the phone I mentioned that I might buy him a plane ticket from Australia to come and give me a hand - I was only kidding as I would never put him to work against his will. A couple of days later my father calls me up, asking when Taleisin is coming out of the water as he’s coming over and give me a hand. Great I’ll have extra hands to do more work. Annie’s father was due in New Zealand shortly after and he is always keen to lend a hand with anything that resembles work. There’s a lot to be said for the older generation’s willingness to work, no matter how soul destroying or miserable it might be. So I started to make a list (oh how naive I was in my younger days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mum and dad arrived the day before haul out. Annie was away on school camp for a few days so I was holding down the fort - well as much as can be expected when people are foolish enough to leave me in charge. In my infinite wisdom I ended up booking the haul out during the biggest classic boat regatta in Auckland - Taleisin should have been part of it. Never mind, it’s booked people are coming to help so I’m locked in. We’ll be back in the water before long, 2 long weekends should be more than enough and with many hands to help it will go quick!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haul out was much less adventurous than I imagined it to be. We simply walked Taleisin into the cradle and had a couple of attempts to get her seated properly. I probably drove the guys in the boat yard nuts as I was concerned at every step of the process. Who wouldn’t be, a boat like Taleisin in irreplaceable. A big thank you to the crew in the boat yard for putting up with me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once Taleisin came out of the water my parents thought I was silly for wanting to haul her and paint the hull, “There’s nothing wrong with it, it looks good”. Then came the mandatory water blasting, again I was very explicit in my instructions, keep the lance far away from the hull, I don’t want any damage from water blasting! While the water blasting process was taking place we could see the anti fouling just flaking off. I’ll be the first to admit that I thought we’d just be fairing in a few bits here and there and then painting over the top to get her back in the water with a nice smooth bottom quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/24368144710/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1540&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c7.staticflickr.com/2/1700/24368144710_bdf0100f5b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1540&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went off to the store to get some supplies to get the sanding started. That’s when the first signs of woes to come started to appear. Touching the anti fouling in some places caused it to flake off, hosing it down with tap pressure only did the same. Other areas it was &lt;strong&gt;stuck&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had to hand sand as they only allowed wet sanding in the yard. It became soul destroying very quickly and there was no visible progress at all. When you get something that looks like it might be faired in some paint would flake off and you start again. Poking and anything makes it worse, sanding in other places makes it worse. This is soul destroying work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t long before I realised that we have to go all the way down to bare teak. This was not the plan! This job is much much bigger than anticipated. So much for the list, now it’s just a matter of getting this one task completed. Taleisin might only be twenty nine and a half feet long, but she’s a HUGE boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I started to make some phone calls to see how much it might cost to get a professional to come and do the job, most refused to touch wooden boats. There was only one man for the job, Alan Boyd from &lt;a href=&quot;http://x-foul-e-8.com&quot;&gt;x-foul-e-8&lt;/a&gt;. The only problem was that Alan was busy and couldn’t come and do the job. Alan was kind enough to come out to Taleisin and provide very good advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Alan advised us on how to proceed we had scrapers to remove the antifouling. Progress was being made, but it was still really slow going. We scraped for 4 days, over the long weekend. Nobody in their right mind would find this even remotely enjoyable. This is really the dark side of boat ownership. I believe it should be mandatory for any would be owner to clean the bottom of the boat he intends to buy first, if you’re still wanting the boat after that you’re good. It would be interesting to see how many people would still go ahead and buy the boat after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the scraping we still had to sand. It was at this point that Annie talked some sense into me and I realised that it would be cheaper for me to be at work while I paid someone else to finish the job. It’s possible that one day I might listen to her up front…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hard part was telling my dad that I’m getting someone else to come and finish the job, my dad is one of those people who refuses to pay someone to do a job he can do himself. I felt guilty having put him to work for 4 days of soul destroying work only to get someone else to finish it up. Thanks Dad for all the hard work, I really do appreciate it, I still feel bad for letting you work that hard only to end up getting someone else to finish the job! In my defence the work was actually far from over, it would have taken us a long time to finish it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few phone calls back and forth I finally managed to get a day that Alan could come and do the work. Suffice to say Alan made it look like it was a walk in the park compared to what we went through. The result was awesome. This did mean that Taleisin was sitting on the hard over the second long weekend with nothing being done too her. I do believe everybody deserved the break though, the job was horrible and the pay was even worse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28152557901/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1545-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8585/28152557901_0c19fd747d_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1545-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28152555031/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1547-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c8.staticflickr.com/8/7632/28152555031_be6cd97d92_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1547-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step was to get painting done. Having learnt my lesson on the paint removal part (also I’ll admit reluctantly that Annie was the sensible one, yet again)… I enlisted the help of professionals for this. They promised me they would start within a day or 2 of Alan finishing his job. This was important as it was during the hottest part of the year (yes lessons have been learnt). Taleisin was starting to dry out and she needed some paint on her bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, as with anything that involves a boat, things take longer than expected. To those well versed in the drill this will come as no surprise, yet somehow I’m surprised every time! The company doing the painting couldn’t start until the following week. While waiting on the painting to start I noticed that the seams are opening. This is not good news for a wooden boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/27949524180/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1548&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8848/27949524180_63ceebde7a_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1548&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I stopped reading online forums, every man and his dog was reporting on my progress on the forums &lt;a href=&quot;http://forums.sailinganarchy.com/index.php?showtopic=171298&amp;amp;hl=taleisin&amp;amp;page=2&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.woodenboat.com/showthread.php?171680-The-Pardeys-are-selling-Taleisin/page2&amp;amp;highlight=Taleisin&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I hit a bit of a panic and of course knowing that the internet is watching I figured I had to do something and quick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled out my phone and started with A in my phone book. I called everybody that I thought might be able and willing to help. I called Annie and told her I was going to bucket salt water onto the hull to get her wet again. By the time Annie arrived (50 minutes or so later) she saw this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/45nt5SM7dj0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this was quite an unexpected evening for most of my friends and family, it was a great relief to have such wonderful friends and family! Most people had a lot of fun, sure it was hard work. It’s not everyday you get to be part of something this crazy though (and when I do crazy, it’s usually on a fairly decent scale)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bucket brigade was a huge success, albeit a little redundant. The next day I drove all over Auckland talking and meeting with boat builders. It turns out that since Taleisin has been in the water for so long, a hose would have done the trick just fine as there’s plenty of salt in the wood. The boat builder had a chuckle and said, “don’t lose any sleep over it”. Lessons learnt, but when you hit a panic you solve a problem with the tools you have at your disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A very special thank you to everybody that answered the call that night, it is very much appreciated!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some panic, running around, getting advice, hiding, and other shenanigans. I finally get around to doing what I should have done in the first place. I bought a lot of shade cloth and hung it around Taleisin. This made a huge difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about 3 weeks on the hard the painting finally got underway. After the primer went on I breathed a sigh of relief! The guys painting Taleisin was great and got a coat of paint on before the 3 weekend started, this made me sleep quite a bit better. As with the guys in the boat yard, these guys had to put up with a lot from me. A big thank you to the team at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.glossboats.co.nz&quot;&gt;Gloss boats&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/27949514230/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1559-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8677/27949514230_bbe7d71275_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1559-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next it was a coat of blue anti foul. The theory is that when we start to see blue on the hull Taleisin is due for a few coats of paint rather than just one coat annually. Time will tell if this is a sound theory or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/27949512700/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1561-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8687/27949512700_7e0d8f23bd_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1561-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally this is followed by two coats in her natural colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28230177665/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1567-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8777/28230177665_e39c9c6270_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1567-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the painting was completed there was one more challenge, a huge storm rolled in. This was a pretty nasty one and a few boats ended on the rocks in the mooring area where we keep Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28230176065/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1569&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8839/28230176065_b68362214d_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1569&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The storm delayed us getting back in the water, which was fine with me. I was actually happier with Taleisin on the hard than in the water. After the storm ran it’s course I was very sad to see that the little boat above was Patricia, a carvel plank H28. She went back in the water just as we came out. Her owner spent a very long time fixing her up to get back in the water. I remember having some banter with him regarding engines. He had to haul Patricia again because there was a leak around the prop shaft - I was a little smug about the fact that Taleisin doesn’t have those kinds of issues. I was heart broken when I saw this though:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/27614521804/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1576-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7499/27614521804_fb3dc51a0b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1576-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After what can only be described as a nightmare of 4 weeks long, we were finally getting the old girl back in the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/28230173915/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1572-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8575/28230173915_c8a367ef2b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1572-2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting Taleisin back on the mooring was rather uneventful or free from adventure if you wish…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days after I had finally got the nerve to give Lin a call, I told her the story. Lin had a chuckle and said: “Taleisin is a tough old boat”, what I should have done was given Lin a call from the start and save myself a lot of worrying. It’s how ever very easy to be reasonable after the fact, hind sight is always 20/20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s taken me quite a while to write about this ordeal, it’s not always easy to face up to your short comings and admit that things weren’t always perfect. This story did have a happy ending, but I can assure you that it was a fairly stressful time for me. I have to admit that the internet was rather kind to me, it could have been so much worse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to everybody who stopped by an offered support and thank you to all those who got roped into helping with something at some point during this adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dont-pick-at-it-youll-only-make-it-worse/&quot;&gt;Don't Pick at It, You'll Only Make It Worse&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on July 11, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guest Blog Post at the Unlikely Boat Builder]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/guest-blog-post-at-the-unlikely-boat-builder/" />
  <id>/guest-blog-post-at-the-unlikely-boat-builder</id>
  <published>2016-04-29T12:57:58+12:00</published>
  <updated>2016-04-29T12:57:58+12:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I’ve written a post. I’ve been quite snowed under with a lot of different projects and my mind was refusing to co-operate. I was asked by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unlikelyboatbuilder.com/&quot;&gt;John Almberg&lt;/a&gt; to write a guest post for his blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably of interest to everybody who’s following us. I wrote about why we bought Taleisin. You can read the post &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unlikelyboatbuilder.com/2016/04/why-did-you-buy-taleisin.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/guest-blog-post-at-the-unlikely-boat-builder/&quot;&gt;Guest Blog Post at the Unlikely Boat Builder&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on April 29, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Did You Buy Taleisin?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/why-we-bought-taleisin/" />
  <id>/why-we-bought-taleisin</id>
  <published>2016-01-23T21:51:16+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-23T21:51:16+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;A simple question, often asked. The answer is not quite as simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying a boat like Taleisin seems like a rather strange thing to do. If you read the forums on the internet you’ll see that people said she’s an old wooden boat with no engine, no market for something like that. So why did we buy her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good question!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this we need to go back in time a little. When I was younger I used to always look at motor yachts, they look sleek and they are loaded with technology. I’m a computer programmer/hacker so naturally it makes sense that I’m attracted to technology. Sailing is archaic and for old guys with lots of time, not to mention that it takes forever to get anywhere. I got caught up in the rat race, worked some horrible jobs over the years got taken advantage of by a few companies and eventually started consulting. This is when I really started to burn the candle at both ends. When you’re working for yourself you usually have the worst boss in the world. How ever during the early years working as a consultant we took a vacation in Fiji, the resort had a couple of Hobi Cat boats that we could sail. I absolutely loved it! I couldn’t get enough of it. But we returned to the real world and that experience faded into a distant memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few more years I was “successful” we had the huge house, the huge mortgage, and it was filled with a huge pile of stuff. At this point I started setting my sighs on a yacht. I was browsing the internet and stared lusting after 57 foot production boats. Bigger is always better…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the researching started. I was fairly committed to a large yacht. I started consuming information on the internet. I’m a compulsive researcher, some say it’s a blessing, others say it’s a curse. I spent hours looking into what makes a good yacht. I started looking at building boats, it doesn’t seem all that complicated and it would certainly be a fun project. Annie put a halt to that pretty quickly when I started measuring the garage to see if I could fit it in there and get it out. I looked at small dinghy plans and at something larger, it would be nice to spend a weekend on it. If your mind works like mine, it won’t be long before you’re at the extreme end of the scale. If at this point you’re thinking, “This guy is all over the place”, you’re right! My mind will make huge leaps and race off into all sorts of different directions, most people get exhausted when they have a conversation with me (I’m working on being less intense). If you’ve done any research on boats and boats that can cross oceans (I was surprised at how small blue water boats can be), it won’t take you long before you come across Lin and Larry Pardey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t long before I was reading the Pardey books. Something changed inside me when I saw the simplicity and what’s achievable on a small budget. I started to have new found existential questions. Why am I on this treadmill? It wasn’t long before I realised that bigger is not better. Doing more research on yachts, now of the Pardey variety. It wasn’t long before I realised that Taleisin was for sale. I couldn’t believe it. The next question on my mind was, “Where is she?” Kawau Island, New Zealand! Checking google maps, it’s close, very close. I fired off an email to the broker stating that I’m interested and would like to have a look, I have a million questions, but without looking at her we won’t know if she’s right for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew that Lin and Larry wouldn’t just sell her to anybody, so I approached it very open and honest. We have hardly any sailing experience, would they sell their baby to a couple of green horns? The broker responded with a reply from Lin, in the email was a phone number and email on which I could reach Lin. Me being a little more old fashioned grabbed the phone and gave Lin a call. I can’t recall the exact conversation, but Lin said something along the lines of “So you’re thinking about becoming a sailor?”, we talked for a while and she was just fantastic. She gave me a lot of good advice, I stated open and honestly that we don’t know if Taleisin is right for us, but we sure would love to come and see her to figure out if she just might be the boat for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lin invited us to Kawau Island for lunch and a tour of the lovely Taleisin. We arranged a date that was well in advance. To put thing into perspective I’ve managed to get Annie to agree to go to the on water boat show a few months earlier, when I did this I was only wanting to have a look. I wasn’t very serious but knew I wanted to get more serious about buying a yacht. The boat show was the weekend before we were supposed to go and see Lin and Larry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the boat show I dragged poor Annie through all the yachts, she wasn’t very happy as she’s not very comfortable around water. She was apprehensive getting on the boats and wouldn’t even go up on the foredeck as it was too narrow for her liking. After the show we talked about the various boats we’d been on, she honestly couldn’t tell them apart. Annie’s comment was, “they were all the same”. She didn’t like them very much, I’m talking about production Jeanneau, Beneteau, Bavaria, and Hanse boats to name a few. We looked at boats starting at 37 foot and moving up to 57 foot. I learnt just how large a 57 foot yacht is (trust me it’s WAY too big for 2 people). The one thing all these boats had in common was their stability. They were bouncing a lot just in the marina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I patiently waited till we managed to make our way to Kawau, on the way there I said to Annie, “now remember, this is an older boat and nothing like the boats we’ve been looking at”. I later found out that Annie was secretly thinking that we’re about to look at a rotting old boat needing a lot of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re familiar with our relationship dynamics you’ll know that Annie leaves me to do all the homework but retains veto power. This allows me to research to my hearts content, get the decision 99% of the way there and then let Annie decide if it’s is right (I get vetoed a lot). This is very important because if she lets me, I’ll make a lot of snap decisions that would probably all be wrong. It’s great to be able to make a decision and then have it verified, it’s sort of a safety net. In many ways Annie is my sanity check, with a mind like mine it’s easy to go down rabbit holes and forget that there’s a top side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming into the cove going past Taleisin I pointed her out to Annie, she smiled and said, “now that’s a NICE boat”. I knew I had a fighting chance here! Getting off the ferry we made our way up to what can only be described as a magnificent little house with magical surroundings. We met Lin and Larry, they were super friendly. Then Lin said, “right lets go play boat”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Off to Taleisin we went! I was quite excited as I had looked at all the photos I could find online. I had even purchased the 5 DVD’s that Lin and Larry made (well the digital versions anyway). I had of course not told Annie how much research I had put into this. In fact I had watched the videos twice by then already. So getting on board this little ship was a very exciting prospect, even though I had already spent a lot of time “aboard”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I noticed was how comfortable Annie was, as soon as she got on deck. She was wondering around very naturally. I quietly mentioned to Lin how this is a first, Annie is NOT comfortable on boats. I was probably grinning ear to ear. Lin took us down below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thoughts were “holy crap she’s small”! Then we sat down in the saloon and Lin started telling us more about her and showing us all the awesome little details they had put into her. The more I looked the more I saw. It didn’t take me long to fall in love with her. I think it went something like this “holy crap she’s small! Look at the detail, she’s awesome. I LOVE this boat, I MUST have her”! It was seconds or less for me to fall in love with Taleisin, this is not the way to buy a boat! I had been warned, Lin even writes about this in her books. My fate was sealed how ever. Lin showed us many things, many things I already knew from doing my homework. I asked what I hope was many good questions. Lin was quite happy to answer all my questions and I’m sure there were coming out rapidly. I don’t doubt that I asked follow up questions before Lin could even finish answering the first question (remember I’m very exhausting to be around at times - I’m working on this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I exhausted Lin we went back to land for lunch and Lin asked us more about ourselves. I explained our current situation and how we’re wanting to change it. Life is over complicated, we want to simplify. Taleisin is awesome, she can teach us about cruising and simplicity. I was again very open and honest about everything. Lin then asked Annie how she felt about it, Annie is quite a bit more reserved about things than I am. Lin could tell that Annie was mulling things over and not as quick to fire as I am. At this point Lin said she would take us out for a sail on Taleisin, but we would have to go and learn the basics first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We bid Lin and Larry farewell and got on the ferry to go home. I think we talked it all over on the way home or even that night. I said to Annie, I really love that boat, I don’t know how you feel about her. Annie told me that Taleisin certainly stood out from the crowd, she had character and was something special. Annie could actually remember details from Taleisin but had no clue as to what the production boats looked like. After some too and fro Annie said, well if you love the boat so much, why don’t you buy her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arranged for sailing lessons as soon as we could fit them in. Annie is a high school teacher and her schedule is very hectic. While all of this is going on Annie had managed to arrange for me to go on a day sail on Steinlarger 2,an 83 foot off shore racing ketch, as part of a group of teachers. The arrangements was made long before we even knew we were going to buy Taleisin. While out sailing on Steinlarger 2 I remember thinking how glad I am that we didn’t buy a bigger boat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I started down the path of putting an offer in. I knew the normal procedure for doing this as I’d been reading a lot of information on the internet. How ever, this was not a normal situation (things hardly ever seems to be normal when I’m involved). I called Lin up and said “I’d like to buy Taleisin, but we have a few complications we need to sort out first…” I did what could only be described as the worlds worst job at negotiating a price, I asked Lin what she’d be willing to accept and that was my offer! To many people thing might seem like a silly strategy, but in my view, buying a boat like Taleisin is something very special, I knew that I wanted to have a good relationship with Lin and Larry and I certainly did not want them to feel like I had driven a hard bargain. This process took place over a few weeks, I had to get some finances sorted and we decided to put our house on the market so we could pay for Taleisin. Selling your house to buy a boat might seem like a strange thing to do. But it felt right, this was a once in a lifetime opportunity that we could not allow to slip away. We had discussed this at length (even though I had already made my mind up within seconds of boarding Taleisin). After explaining the challenge ahead of myself to Lin (again probably not a very good strategy, but I believe in transparency and honesty), We came to an arrangement of a long settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after agreeing the whole deal with Lin, I put in an offer through the broker (remember how I said nothing is normal when I get involved). The whole process was rather straight forward since we’d already agreed on the terms. It was also very pleasant! The next step was to arrange the survey. I called around and asked many people who would be a good surveyor. Eventually someone told me Ray Beale is the best there is for this kind of boat. I called Ray up and arranged for him to come and survey Taleisin. I went out to Kawau to witness the survey. I arrived early so I could help Lin put Taleisin on the tidal grid (we had many phone conversations leading up to this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we put Taleisin on the tidal grid I had to wait for Ray to arrive. Lin was kind enough to leave me to my own devices (maybe she was smart enough to know that I’ll be firing a million questions her way if she was within earshot). I was in and out of Taleisin, inspecting and investigating as much as I could. There’s a LOT to investigate on Taleisin (I’m still learning about new things I didn’t know about almost 18 months after I first set foot on her). From time to time Lin would come and check on me and I’d fire off a few questions, listening carefully to the answers so I can remember them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was super excited and it took the entire day. I was asking a million questions listening to everything Ray had to say. Taking on board as much as I can and trying to short circuit the learning process by taking advantage of the decades of experience I was surrounded with. I’m very fortunate that my most important asset is my natural ability to learn, learn quickly and on the fly (it helps tremendously with the day job), I’m usually pretty good at applying things after that too. I talked to Ray after it was all done and we were back on the main land. The comment he made was something along the lines of, “you couldn’t have picked a better boat of that construction if you tried”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So pretty much knowing the survey would come back good I was getting ready for the next step, the sea trial. I can’t recall exactly when we had our sailing lessons, as with anything I’m learning I had already studied so much about sailing online and in books that by the time we had lessons I was well ahead of the class. I had a blast, the boat we learnt on was a 47 foot sloop, again I recall thinking I’m glad we bought a smaller boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually we went out for the sea trial. It was awesome. Everything on Taleisin is people sized. Everything is simple and easy to handle. It took a while for us to get all our ducks in a row, but we were not backing out of the deal, Taleisin was ours we just had to get all the pieces in the right place. I was reading internet forums well before I even saw Taleisin, I read all the things people posted on the forums but decided to make up my own mind. I have no doubt that there’a a lot of people out there thinking that we paid too much for an old wooden boat with no engine, and those people are right - to them she is just an old wooden boat with no engine. To us, even though we were not sailors at the time, she was a magnificent creation. Built like nothing else, safe, simple and pure joy to be aboard. Making things simple is not easy, Taleisin is simple, this is very valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lin invited us to stay aboard Taleisin to see what it would be like to spend the night on her. I can’t recall the exact order of events, but I do know we spent quite a bit of time staying on Taleisin on the mooring. It just felt right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleisin contains 40+ years of real hardcore cruising experience, these are things we don’t have to figure out for ourselves. Being able to pick up the phone and call Lin with questions is also very valuable. The price we paid for Taleisin was not just for an old wooden boat, we gained so much more out of the deal. In all honesty Taleisin is worth a lot more than we paid for her in materials alone, the labour to build her is not even factored in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more space in Taleisin than I realised at first. This is a very big little boat. The photos and the videos of Taleisin does not do her justice. She’s so much more in the flesh. Something else that’s very nice about Taleisin is that she’s alive. She has character. Her planks are infused with Lin and Larry’s soul, when I look around her and touch her you can see and feel Lin and Larry everywhere. There’s so much history, so many adventures. Being on board Taleisin is magical, I know it’s still early days but I hope we can do her justice and add to her legacy. Taleisin will no doubt outlive both Annie and myself (she’s that well constructed), all we have to do is look after her. We don’t do anything lightly, we know the world has eyes on us. We want to do what’s right for Taleisin, the thought of making holes in her pains both of us. We have not made any alterations to her. When we had her on the hard there were many tense moments (more about that in a future post). I know that Lin told me that she’s our boat and we can do as we please with her, but when you own something that’s got a soul it’s difficult to do something that goes against her very being. We enjoy looking after her, being forced to think about things before we do them is a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleisin might not be perfect, but she’s perfect for us!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/why-we-bought-taleisin/&quot;&gt;Why Did You Buy Taleisin?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 23, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Defeated in the Marina]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/defeated-in-the-marina/" />
  <id>/defeated-in-the-marina</id>
  <published>2016-01-22T20:56:04+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-22T20:56:04+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been contemplating posting this story for some time, clearly this is not one of my finest moments. I’ve decided to share it because other’s find it entertaining, and it might be a cautionary tale to would be engineless sailors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is normal for me, when I get a new toy I want to use it. At this point we’ve owned Taleisin for a few weeks. I’ve been out on her once with Chad from the CYA. He showed me how to barge using Cheeky and the 2.5hp motor, and he also taught me how to scull. Chad is super experienced, I didn’t do the whole procedure myself and I don’t have any “what if” plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came up with a plan, if 2.5hp can do it, I can get an inflatable with a bigger engine and that should make things much easier. So I go shopping, I get a 2.6m Zodiac and an 8hp outboard. Armed with a new sure fire way to get Taleisin in and out of the marina I study the weather forecasts and pick a day that seems like it would be perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get up early on Saturday morning, I’m very excited - like a little kid on christmas morning. When I’m excited about things, I don’t hide it very well - everybody knows. Annie mentioned to me in the car on the way to the marina that she can tell that it’s one of those excited days for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we’re onboard at the marina I start putting the inflatable together (I now seem to call her Ducky). I attached some lines to Ducky, dropped her in the water and started to tie her to the quarter. Keep in mind this was pretty much winter time in New Zealand so I was wearing foul weather gear and thermals underneath them. It’s taken quite a bit longer to set everything up, which I now know is normal for everything boat related. Eventually we get Taleisin ready for sailing and start to go over “the plan”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the plan, Annie asks? We drop the mooring lines, I put the outboard in reverse. We back out slowly, use Taleisin’s rudder to steer and then get out of here. Lets just give it a go. That’s fine, Annie said, but the wind has picked up a bit…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be fine, I said…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We dropped the mooring lines, I put the outboard in reverse and Taleisin backs out slowly. All is going great so far. Watch out behind you, said Annie, that boat is getting closer. I look behind me. I put the outboard in forward. We move forward. Move the tiller to the other side we need to turn. It’s not working, says Annie. The wind was blowing the bow off. We’re going to hit in front Annie yells. Back in reverse. We do this a few times. While we’re doing this the wind is blowing us sideways down the channel. “Take the dingy and go push on the bow”, yells a spectator. What he didn’t know is that I made a fatal mistake and secured the dinghy a bit too well and there was no way I would be able to untie it in time. This was completely and utterly stupid of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to just gun the outboard. We need to pick up way so we can turn. That’s what the problem is. We’re still not turning. Back in reverse, gun it! Whoops that boat behind me is getting close. I hit a piling with the stern anchor - I’ve bent it slightly but it will survive. At this point I think that it might be a good idea to go forward. By now the bow is in a much better position and we might actually get out. I reach for the gear lever on the outboard and flick it to forward…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I say we’ll be fine? I was wrong…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except for the fact that I didn’t close the throttle while almost at full speed. Big mistake. Rookie Mistake. The dingy still tied to the quarter lifts it’s bow out of the water and stands up right, I try to hang onto the seat. No luck. The outboard gets drowned. I end up in the water. Taleisin is still heading for the boats in front of her. Annie thinking quickly and with a bit of guidance from the audience we’ve now assembled on the dock, sprints up the bowsprit, grabs the forestay, both feet up against the boat in front of us. She fends like a champ!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No crash yet, that’s good right. While all of this is happening I’m in the water. Thinking to myself “oh crap, I have to get back on board because this is going south fast”. Hanging off the side of Taleisin I quickly drag myself up to the bow so I can get up on the bobstay to climb back on board. Another spectator on the dock yells, get your motor going! I hop in Ducky, try to get her started, no luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I get back on board I see one of our neighbors motoring out to come and rescue us. “Throw me a line”, he yells! “I’ll tow you into the channel, no worries mate”! I declined and opted to go back to the slip. “I killed the motor, no idea how I’ll get back”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as we’re pulling into the slip the marina boat shows up. I quietly say to Annie, I’m in a lot of trouble now, they wont be happy about this. I had a sheepish look on my face and was very apologetic about the whole thing. Everybody just smiled and said “that’s boating, it won’t be your last…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I’m feeling pretty well defeated. I’ve been defeated in the past, but NEVER like this. Usually there’s some upside to the defeat for me. I honestly could not find an upside, nothing went well. I did a bunch of really dumb things, and I couldn’t even try to deny it. The results spoke for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The marina boat crew and our rescue crew just had a chuckle and were on their way. We did give our rescuer a pack of beers as a thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outboard seemed to be fine when I got it home and started it, I had a small win. I was moping around for a few days not quite knowing how to deal with this defeat. My tail was firmly tucked between my legs. I started reading up on warping techniques and other engineless maneuvers. It took me a while to build up the courage to take Taleisin out again. I did have a perfect excuse though, winter was in full swing and the weather was pretty nasty. My research paid off, eventually, we moved Taleisin to her mooring on our own without too much trouble. I should probably listen to Annie more, but my stubbornness seems to get the better of me at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to leave a comment with your own experiences. I think I’ve recovered from the trauma inflicted upon my ego, you’re allowed to have a laugh at my expense. Looking forward to hearing from anybody who reads this.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/defeated-in-the-marina/&quot;&gt;Defeated in the Marina&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 22, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ditching Work to Go Sailing...]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/ditching-work-to-go-sailing/" />
  <id>/ditching-work-to-go-sailing</id>
  <published>2016-01-20T16:24:28+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-20T16:24:28+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;So you wake up in the morning, it’s perfect weather, the wind is just enough to move the boat at a slow pace. You think to yourself, “excellent, lets to sailing”. Suddenly you realise it’s Tuesday morning and you’re supposed to be at work for meetings. So you make a decision….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did attend the required meetings and told everybody in the office, that’s it, I’m going sailing see you tomorrow! I went home, had a quick lunch and loaded Ducky in the car. Annie and I were off to the dock…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very fortunate that I can at times have flexibility around working hours, most of the time we’re very busy and I have to keep my nose to the grindstone. I’m working towards freeing more time up for playing. Annie is a school teacher and she’s fortunately still on holiday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re becoming more efficient at getting away from the dock. We were motoring towards Taleisin in Ducky in no time at all. Once onboard Taleisin we got her prepped for sailing, we looked at each other. We each took a deep breath. I hoisted the main sail. We cast off the mooring line. Taleisin fell off the wind. The main sail filled and we were sailing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/24141559759/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1517&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1467/24141559759_ca80f35045_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1517&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we built up a little way Annie hoisted the stays’l, I sheeted it in and Taleisin was moving well. We only set the stays’l since we just wanted to sail at a snails pace and enjoy the water. We were not going fast but it was glorious!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23881140514/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1518&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1660/23881140514_16466c906b_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1518&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we were moving slowly and just kicking back Annie went down below to get her fishing rod. She sat on the cabin top happily trawling while we’re moving slowly through the water. I could tell by the look on her face that she was quite content. I should point out that she was fishing and directing me where to go etc…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23881375394/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1520&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1576/23881375394_afa50b1157_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1520&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Annie was trying to catch dinner I was happily sailing the boat and tacking back and forth on my own. I’m sure it was less than impressive but I wanted to experiment and it was fun and non threatening. It felt like a great opportunity to do some learning. We didn’t spend a huge amount of time out, maybe an hour or two. Then is was time to head back to the mooring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23882532203/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1522&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1476/23882532203_c1fd3dc935_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1522&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23881134184/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1521&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1506/23881134184_eb69c94f35_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1521&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we got closer to the mooring field we decided to drop the stays’l and sail in under the main only. In theory that sounded like it would work, but the current was stronger than our drive under main only. Realising the error in our ways we had the stays’l up again and made our way into the mooring field. We dropped the stays’l again and attempted to approach the mooring from down wind. Things didn’t work out that well. Annie said, umm that boat behind us is getting closer. The boat was not moving, we were going backwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran forward hoisted the stays’l, yelled “sheet it in”! Taleisin picked up way again and Annie was able to steer us clear of the few surrounding boats. While she was doing this I moved quickly and maybe in a slight panic to get Ducky tied on the quarter and get the engine running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the engine started to push Taleisin I dropped the sails. Annie said, “The boats not turning the right way”! Due to the fact that the engine is pushing her in the other direction. I responded, “then turn the other way”! Annie moved the tiller, Taleisin responded and we steered well clear of all other boats. In reality we were never anywhere near any of these boats they were actually well clear of us - it just felt like they were getting closer. We probably had a few boat lengths between us at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great, now we have control of the situation! “Where’s the mooring buoy?”, I asked. Annie pointed it out and we slowly pushed Taleisin towards it. While doing this is became obvious that the wind wants to blow the bow off and just using the tiller alone was not going to do the trick. I started experimenting and learning again. I found that if I moved the outboard tiller all the way over I can use it like a stern thruster and quickly point the bow in a different direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tried to get to the mooring buoy, no luck, the current keeps pushing us off. “Approach it so the current pushes you onto the mooring”, says Annie, “Like I’ve already told you to do”. So we gave that a try, it worked, easily. I grabbed the buoy and tied a line to it so I could in theory relax and deal with things in a calm manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nice idea, I still felt the need to haul the mooring line over the bow roller, tied another line through the attachment loop and secured it around a winch. “Let’s get this thing secured”, after a bit of effort we managed to get the mooring attached securely. I turned to Annie and gave her a high five, “success, we did it”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will confess that my adrenaline spiked and I was less than cool calm and collected. Annie was a champ, she never missed a beat! I needed to sit down and collect myself. I also had the greatest feeling of accomplishment as I sat on the foredeck! Who knew that something this simple can feel this satisfying! Is this what is meant by enjoying the simpler things in life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tidied Taleisin up, Annie put some salt water on the deck. We loaded Ducky up and went back to the dock. Once we were tied up I remember thinking, “Wow, I didn’t loose anything overboard”. That was a bad thought. Just as I lifted the outboard from Ducky I noticed the trim rod was lose and hanging out. I tried to put the motor down to get it and at the moment it fell out and I watched it sink in the water. This is just ridiculous! At this rate I’ll have nothing left to lose soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went home, content with yet another adventure provided by Taleisin, she surely is turning out to be an adventure machine.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ditching-work-to-go-sailing/&quot;&gt;Ditching Work to Go Sailing...&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 20, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sailing in Cheeky]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/sailing-in-cheeky/" />
  <id>/sailing-in-cheeky</id>
  <published>2016-01-18T21:33:12+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-18T21:33:12+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;“Let’s go sailing in the dinghy” was the words that Annie uttered on a Saturday morning. The weather was wonderful and there was not a lot of wind. She was excited about the prospect of sailing in the dinghy. I was thinking to myself, this is huge, Annie is pushing &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; to go sailing. So we loaded the car up with Cheeky’s oars and small 2.5hp outboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting cheeky launched was quick and easy and we were on our way out to Taleisin in no time. You might be wondering why we’re going to Taleisin if we’re dinghy sailing!? The answer is simple, of course, Cheeky’s mast, rudder, drop board, tiller and sail is onboard Taleisin. Once we got to Taleisin we grabbed everything we needed to rig cheeky for sailing and went back to the dock to rig her up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we got back to the dock I spent a bit of time trying to figure out how to make this little boat sail. Granted I don’t know much about boats and sailing, it didn’t take much to figure out a way to get the pieces to fit so it can sail. I was quite surprised at the simplicity. Lin once said to me that a sailboat is an incredibly simple machine, and I guess you can be excused for thinking otherwise looking at modern yachts loaded to the gunwales with complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So having the boat rigged up and ready to attempt to sail her I went back to the car to store the outboard motor. I returned to the dock and we cast off to go sailing. We had a slight problem, no wind. Don’t worry, Annie said look there are boats sailing out there, pointing to the harbor, lets just row out for a bit until we can catch a breeze. So Annie being the champ that she is, grabbed the oars and started to row us out! It didn’t take long before the sail filled and we started sailing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were moving slowly, but we were moving. It was very nice and relaxing, we went out into the channel of the harbor, tacked back and forth for about an hour and then we decided to head back for lunch. We slowly sailed through the mooring field and back to the dock. Annie asked if we should row back to the dock, but me being as stubborn as a mule wanted to sail back. Slowly but surely we made it back to the dock and gently docked Cheeky under sail. It was a small victory, but we did dock under sail. It certainly is nothing like it would be docking Taleisin, but it was an achievement none the less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos weren’t high priority for us, here’s a couple of bad “selfies”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23864001004/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1514&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1489/23864001004_e58fabac29_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1514&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/24196634050/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1516&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1444/24196634050_998d234e74_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1516&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safely back at the dock we started to disassemble cheeky and moved her back to the dinghy rack. Where’s the car keys, I asked Annie? We looked everywhere for the keys. We couldn’t find the car keys! I asked around to see if anybody would know where they might get handed in if anybody found them. I eventually get hold of the on site security guard. She was a lovely lady, very friendly, and helpful. After a bit of looking around and digging through everything the security guard asked if she could call us a tow truck to come and open the car, at this point I thought I may have locked them in the car when I put the outboard away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the tow truck underway and me cursing under my breath as to how stupid I am, I ran into the crew from Pinch of Salt. I enquired as to the whereabouts of their dinghy. Apparently they have located it on TradeMe (the New Zealand version of E-Bay) and was trying to figure out how to get it back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tow truck arrives, the driver takes 3 seconds to open the door. No keys in the car, bugger! We paid the driver the $80 fee for his services. What happened next was unexpected and a nice surprise. The driver offered to drive us home to get our spare key for the car. We quickly loaded everything into the car, locked it up and accepted the kind offer with a smile!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we arrived home we had another challenge! The key to the house was attached to the key for the car. We’re in luck we have a locksmith around the corner from us, a very friendly guy and also a sailor (well this is Auckland, almost everybody is a sailor). I wondered over to see if he was home. Slight problem, he was out fishing for the day, but his lovely wife suggested that their 18 year old son bring the ladder around and climb through the window we left open. Success! We got inside, got the spare key and went back to the dock in our other car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our way back to the dock Annie suggested that we stop and get a cold drink and ice-cream for the security guard that was so helpful and friendly. It was nice to put a smile on her face and she really appreciated it as the sun was beating down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So naturally after we got home, I posted a little about this experience on cruisers forum. One of the members pointed out that it might pay to sacrifice some coins upfront to the ocean as it would appear that I’m paying for safe passage one way or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great time, and it was another adventure thanks to Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sailing-in-cheeky/&quot;&gt;Sailing in Cheeky&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 18, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mooring Under Sail]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/mooring-under-sail/" />
  <id>/mooring-under-sail</id>
  <published>2016-01-06T16:40:39+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-06T16:40:39+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;We got up early today to go sailing on Taleisin! We loaded the car with our inflatable training wheels and made our way to the dock. We started going through the motions of assembling the ducky to transport us out to Taleisin. The reason we had to get up early was to make our way out to Taleisin to collect another life jacket. The extra life jacket was for Bud, a classic sail maker in Auckland from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.naldersails.com&quot;&gt;Nalder sails&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve been told that Bud is an expert in the field of classic sail making, he’s an old salt and absolutely loves the classics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On board Taleisin we started to get her ready to go sailing, undoing the sail covers, running the sheets, putting the tiller in place, the usual things you do before you go sailing. Bud called to tell me he’s running a little late. We were fine with that as we were just hanging out on Taleisin and it was a nice day. Unfortunately for us Taleisin is moored in a spot where the sea state is exactly right to induce motion sickness. Annie had already taken sea legs and was just chilling out on the foredeck, I on the other hand, had not and started to feel the effects of sea sickness setting. This was mostly due to me playing with the y-valve in the galley for the drain. Rookie mistake, I know. The smell coming out of it was something awful and made my stomach churn. Luckily I’ve been reading about this stuff and decided to get up on deck quickly. After some fresh air I went down below looking for sea legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll have to use your imagination as I didn’t take any photos, but there I was laying down in the cockpit trying to regain my composure. At this point I thought it might be best if I headed back to the dock to gain some stability back! I left Annie on board Taleisin, grabbed an extra life jacket, jumped in the ducky and went back to the dock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting at the dock things were getting much better quickly and I forgot all about that nasty y-valve incident. While waiting a couple of young sailors walked up and asked me if the dinghy tied to the dock belonged to me. After a bit of conversation they explained how they went out for a sail the previous day and the tow rope on their dinghy sheared through. The offered to pay me some money to ferry them to their boat. I politely declined the offer for money (seemed like it would be bad karma to accept money for something this simple) and suggested that if they just hang around till Bud arrives that I’ll gladly drop them off on their yacht, Pinch of Salt. I do have to give these guys credit, they were about to swim out to their yacht with all their provisions on a float. They would how ever have to swim back to the dock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bud arrived, all for of us piled into Ducky with all the provisions too. Off we went! The crew of Pinch of Salt was happy once aboard and we continued on our way to Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once on board Taleisin we hanked on the jib. Bud asked me if I wanted to leave under sail instead of hip towing. My answer was “of course”! Bud explained the procedure and what he expected Taleisin to do while we’re doing this. Basically Taleisin is so sea kindly and well balanced that we hoisted the main, cast the mooring line off and she just fell off the wind and we were sailing under main only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we got outside the mooring field we hoisted the stays’l and she picked up speed. The jib on Taleisin is on a separate stay from the forestay, this was done so that Lin and Larry could deal with the jib without having to go out on the bowsprit while rounding Cape Horn. We didn’t tighten this properly because the mooring line was over the rope gypsy while we were moored. I was having a bit of fun and games up on the bow trying to sort this out while under way. I can say this, I’m very glad that Larry put 8 inch bulwarks all around Taleisin’s deck, it certainly made life a LOT easier on the bow. To add insult to injury I didn’t sort the down haul for the jib out properly so I was running back and forth trying to hoist the jib. After screwing around for probably a good 5-10 minutes with this I finally managed to get the jib up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to the cockpit, we sheeted the jib in, put Taleisin hard on the wind. It was glorious! It’s the first time we’ve had Taleisin under full sail! I had the biggest grin on my face and so did Bud - not sure which of us was having more fun! Annie was hanging out in the companion way for most of the duration, only jumping out to help with sheets when we were tacking of gybing. While Annie is no stranger to adventure and extreme sports, she’s a much better rock climber than I am, she’s not comfortable on the water at all. She should be commended for agreeing to buy Taleisin and to sail with me, she is absolutely amazing because she will push herself well out of her comfort zone and perform much better than I ever could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After tacking back and forth up wind Bud suggested we gybe and come up alongside one of the old New Zealand America’s cup yachts. That was a bit of fun, but they left us behind rather quickly! Bud showed me how to get Taleisin to run downwind wing and wing. This will take some practice to do confidently!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we knew it we were back at the mooring field and Bud was explaining how to come in under sail. Bud made this look super easy! We rounded up slowly and ghosted onto the mooring buoy, I grabbed it with the boat hook and then the fun started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was quite a bit more load on the line than expected, I couldn’t just hold Taleisin in place, Annie came up to the bow and asked if she could help. I said get me a line so I can tie this damn thing off. Looking back I should have taken a turn on something with the line and it would have been a lot less exciting! We got it tied off. I put a line through the bow roller and around the windlass rope gypsy. Bud and myself heaved the mooring line up and we managed to tie the line through the mooring line’s loop. We ended up winching the rest in and eventually got the mooring line secured. This was probably the hardest part of the whole experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all of that done we tidied Taleisin up and we spent a bit of time discussing Taleisin’s new sails. I think it’s safe to say that we’re very excited about the new sails, they should look absolutely awesome and Taleisin will have more of a classic look with them than she does now. This might be a bit counter to what Lin and Larry would have done, but I don’t think they will mind too much, it’s all about making the old girl look really good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dinghy ride back was not quite as good. I’m a pretty average dinghy helmsman and got the entire crew wet in the chop. In spite of all of this Bud was kind enough to agree to mentor us on how to do things under sail! This is a huge relief as doing things without an engine and learning that way is quite tough on your own when you’re not entirely sure what you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming months Bud will produce new sails for Taleisin, we’ll be sure to take some pictures of her with the new sails…&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mooring-under-sail/&quot;&gt;Mooring Under Sail&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 06, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Windlass spring]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/windlass-spring/" />
  <id>/windlass-spring</id>
  <published>2016-01-04T14:33:36+13:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-04T14:33:36+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This might seem like a strange post. In fact it is. I was contacted by John, who needed to know the dimensions of a particular spring in Taleisin’s Windlass. He’s got the same Windlass and the spring is in pieces. I figured that I’d post this as it just might come in handy for someone else in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up, here’s the plastic pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23792203469/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1474&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1441/23792203469_cc43ed49e2_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;516&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1474&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve read the strength of a spring is determined by:&lt;br /&gt;
1. Wire diameter&lt;br /&gt;
2. Outer diameter&lt;br /&gt;
3. Free Length (length of spring)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
4. Number of total coils&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wire diameter: 0.7 mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23531821304/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1478&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1693/23531821304_89d16574b9_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1478&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outer diameter: 5mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23531821304/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1478&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1693/23531821304_89d16574b9_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1478&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free length: 39.9mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/24160019885/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1476&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1600/24160019885_1f0264c0ce_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1476&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I counted 57 coils, also 39.9 / 0.7 = 57&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also measured the ends: 26.4mm (but this might be a little bit off as I didn’t remove the screw).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/23864397880/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1479&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1559/23864397880_8914e58bef_c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1479&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a calculator that might be of use: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acxesspring.com/extension-spring-calculator-instructions.html&quot;&gt;Calculator - external link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimate of length inside “hooks” 92.360 mm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need more accuracy, let me know, and I’ll take screws out and measure it correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/windlass-spring/&quot;&gt;Windlass spring&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on January 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving Day...]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/moving-day/" />
  <id>/moving-day</id>
  <published>2015-10-29T20:56:22+13:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-29T20:56:22+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;We woke up in the morning, I said to Annie “if we’re going to move Taleisin today, we better get going. Not much wind but it will pick up later today”. You might wonder, move Taleisin where? Taleisin has been sitting snugly in the marina all winter, as you might imagine getting an 8 ton engineless boat out of a marina can be a little challenging. We have recently had a new mooring laid in a spot that’s easy to sail on and off. This is where Taleisin is moving to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve had some previous attempts at getting out of the marina, one didn’t go to well and the other turned into a warping practice run. I might write about the first attempt one day but the bruises are still visible on my ego. In short, I ended up in the water and I drowned an outboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in preparation for our adventure, we prepared Taleisin for sailing, talked through our plan, had a disagreement, came to an agreement and we were finally ready to give it a “go”. We did all of this in just 2 hours. Given previous experience I’d be lying if I said that I wasn’t nervous, but I had to hide this from Annie as it would make her more nervous, she was already not that confident in my ability to pull this little stunt off. Not being one to shy away from a challenge, I just dragged my feet for a little bit building up the courage to give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people have asked me in the past how we deal with the lack of an engine, here’s the current way of doing things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Warp out of the berth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strap the dingy to the quarter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;barge out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warp1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Getting ready to warp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the warp lines around the pilings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warp2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Getting ready to warp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pulled her out slowly using the mooring lines (not in the diagram).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warp3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Getting ready to warp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annie was in the cockpit pulling on the stern line to turn the boat. I was on the bow pulling the boat closer to avoid the bow sprit hitting the pilings. This was something that happened the first time we tried to warp out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/warp4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Getting ready to warp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that the direction the boat is pointing in is the direction of the channel. We tied the dingy to the hip and barged out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s worth noting a few things that we learned from this. Firstly we warped her out really well, it felt great! However, do not put the dingy on the opposite side of the pilings. While there’s no way on, the dingy will push the boat into the pilings (there was no wind to push us off the pilings). Consequently we had a lot of fending to do, this is hard work if you’re moving a heavy boat. Once you have way on (and Taleisin doesn’t need much), it’s very easy to move the boat in this manner! The original plan was to push off the pilings and drift into the middle of the channel, unfortunately this didn’t work out. Next time I’d get the dingy between the boat the and pilings (still need to figure out how we’d go about this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few gut busting seconds later Taleisin was moving fast enough for the rudder to be effective! I looked at Annie raised a fist in the air and said, the hard part is over! Annie obviously didn’t share my victory as we still had to navigate our way out of the marina and into the harbour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally making it out of the marina, Annie commented how she’s very glad to be out of the marina as it’s been nothing but unpleasant boating experience inside it. I can completely understand her point of view as it’s been super challenging and we kept getting beaten down by Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next challenge was to hoist the sails, luckily we picked a day with very little wind. Annie went forward and hoisted the main, it didn’t seem to move us… The next minute a powerboat came speeding by at what was definitely in excess of 12 knots (harbour limits). The wake nearly tipped the dingy and almost drowned the outboard. I leapt over the life lines and onto the dingy to keep it upright. We traveled under motor a little bit longer but the power boats were traveling way too fast and it felt like we were inside a washing machine. I cut the outboard and let the dingy trail behind. I hoisted the staysail and went to sit in the cockpit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ghetto sounder/chart plotter indicated that we were traveling at 1-2 knots. Since it didn’t really feel like we had much in the way of steerage I can only assume that the current was pushing us along. It was interesting to see how quickly Annie’s dislike for power boats grew as we were drifting, she’s a proper sailor now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After drifting for a while and getting thrown around by power boat wakes for too long Annie persuaded me to put the dingy back on the quarter and push Taleisin towards the mooring. Once I got the dingy pushing along we actually saw 5 knots on the Dragonfly pro, I’m guessing at least 1-2 of those were current related. It’s worth noting that the outboard was only at half throttle and only 8HP. Now that we were moving we were making great progress, I also didn’t have to sit in the dingy the whole way and could just steer with the rudder on Taleisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approaching the mooring I hopped into the dingy and slowed the engine down, when we got close enough I just let the engine idle and we kept moving slowly towards the buoy. Pickup was a breeze. There was only one problem, this was not our mooring. Since it’s a new mooring and we’ve never used it we didn’t know what to look for. But the mooring number was not the number I was given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So rather than panic I got the engine pushing along slowly again and Annie steered us towards another buoy. We followed the same recipe as before and pickup was very easy again! We secured Taleisin to the mooring and had a high five moment!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you’re reading along and thinking that’s the end of the adventure you would be forgiven since for most it probably would be. We’re not most and this is when we got seasick for no apparent reason. Taleisin was rolling quite a bit, we still can’t figure out why. I was telling myself to just push through and get everything stashed away and tidied up. Annie lay down on the foredeck and it looked like a good idea to me. We spent about an hour just laying there feeling pretty horrible. I’d get up from time to time trying to keep on working but I didn’t have much luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually Annie felt well enough to get back to work, when I got up to try and help I got instructed to lay back down as I was apparently not looking the best. Annie soldiered on like a champ and put Taleisin in order!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had one task that we needed to do before we could head for the dock, get cheeky&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; off her chocks. I had a few attempts at this and eventually managed to get the job done without going green completely! Once this task was done we loaded up the dingy with everything we needed to take back with us, then we learnt something interesting….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as we got on the dingy the seasickness was gone. Since the motion of the dingy was different to the motion of Taleisin we felt better, next time I’m getting in the dingy! Motoring back to the dock we were towing Cheeky&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, eventually getting back to the dock the packing up and loading the car up took a while. Approximately 8 hours after we started we finished by stopping for lunch on the way back to the marina to collect our mooring lines and other car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/22393527820/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;DSC_5316&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/571/22393527820_60f6855283_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;681&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_5316&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something as simple as moving from the marina to a mooring turned into an adventure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting here after having written this whole post and the previous sentence I’m reminded of something that Lin told us before we bought Taleisin: “This is not a boat, it’s an adventure machine”. Lin was right, Taleisin definitely is an adventure machine, even mundane tasks become adventures!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/moving-day/&quot;&gt;Moving Day...&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on October 29, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ghetto Depth Sounder]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/ghetto-depth-sounder/" />
  <id>/ghetto-depth-sounder</id>
  <published>2015-10-24T21:52:43+13:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-24T21:52:43+13:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Learning to sail a boat like Taleisin is challenging at best, learning to sail on a boat like Taleisin takes things up a notch! Training wheels! That’s what we need! While Taleisin has got a perfectly good lead line on board (still functioning as well as the day the Pardeys installed it), we’ve got plenty to get right without the worry about how deep the water is. Enter the Raymarine Dragonfly 4 Pro, now don’t get me wrong, there’s no substitute for common sense and we fully intend on moving to old school navigation and old school depth sounding. Baby steps are normally the way to start, jumping in the deep end with a boat like Taleisin provides plenty of challenge without the added bits around the edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after spending some time searching around and scratching my head I came up with this little design. It’s a 25mm PVC pipe with a 20mm dowel shoved down the inside. It’s a prototype, the idea is that the dowel prevents the flex, and PVC is pretty well suited to being in water. I still need to seal the bottom of it using some silicon or epoxy or what ever will do the job. It should be quite obvious to the observer that we don’t intend on putting a through hull transducer on Taleisin and that this is just a “portable” sounder and chart plotter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/22243349589/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1337&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/663/22243349589_36106320d1_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1337&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lashing the pipe to the transom as a temporary measure, I will do this slightly better before I take it out for a test sail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/22404136546/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1338&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5703/22404136546_d38cf9aa86_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;768&quot; height=&quot;1024&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1338&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fashioned some form of plug and play system using an existing 12V plug in Taleisin. We’re not very keen on altering Taleisin without having thought it through properly. This allows me to play and if I choose to throw it out, nobody will know any better (well maybe they will if they read this post). I guess I’m trying to say that the boat will not be harmed with this little experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/22242426758/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1341&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5785/22242426758_6bab8d10a8_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;768&quot; height=&quot;1024&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1341&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an added little bonus, it’s got a GPS chart plotter for added entertainment. This will provide a makeshift set of instrumentation for speed, depth and GPS. While I could have used an iPad - and I thought about it, using some wifi type transducer with the Navionics app. This would have left me with the small issue that it’s not waterproof. After doing a lot of reading I ended up going with the dragonfly instead, added bonus is that I can connect the iPad via wifi and still have a larger screen. I also think I might get better battery life out of the dragonfly than the iPad, but time will tell!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sdki/22404132386/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;IMG_1339&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5650/22404132386_e7530ce891_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1339&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How will all of this work out? I have no idea, but if it works it will allow some training wheels during the early stages. Once we get up to standard with our skills it wont matter any more.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ghetto-depth-sounder/&quot;&gt;Ghetto Depth Sounder&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on October 24, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sailing Taleisin for the First Time]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/sailing-taleisin-for-the-first-time/" />
  <id>/sailing-taleisin-for-the-first-time</id>
  <updated>2015-10-24T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2015-10-22T22:15:33+13:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Eben and Annie</name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This story begins early the previous morning. We had to drive 1 hour to Sandspit to catch the ferry which would drop us off on the Pardey’s jetty. Once we got there we rowed out to Taleisin like we have done a few times in the past. We loaded our personal belongings onto Taleisin, only what we needed to survive for the next 2 days. This meant we had some food and warm clothes should the weather require it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After loading our personal belongings on the boat we spent some time with Lin in the boat workshop. She spent quite a while explaining what all the bits and pieces are that we should be loading onto Taleisin. There was a big pile of it, I remember asking Lin where it would all fit. Lin assured me that it’s all been on Taleisin and that she will swallow it without any issues. After going through everything in detail we began the long day of ferrying everything to Taleisin via Cheeky&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. I had a discussion with Lin about the weather forecast as some heavy weather was forecast for the afternoon. We decided that we’ll set sail early in the morning and we should hopefully beat the bad weather, it’s only about 30 nautical miles to sail. Loading Taleisin took a very long and time we were absolutely exhausted as we finished the last load in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got up as early as we could manage, had a quick breakfast and started to prepare Taleisin to set sail. I rigged up a GoPro and set it to record while this was going on. Underestimating the battery life on the GoPro it ran out of power long before things got exciting. Below is an edit of some of the footage, there’s not much going on but it will give you an idea of what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yCuMyVlxJ3A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something to keep in mind, Annie and I have never sailed a big boat on our own. We’ve had some sailing lessons, been on a couple of sailing trips with people who are experienced. That was about the extent of our sailing experience on big boats. I’m very fortunate that my day job requires me to learn things very quickly, retain them, and put them to use almost immediately. This skill came in very handy when it was time to sail Taleisin out of the cove. Taleisin does not have an engine, this means there’s a bonus challenge when it comes to sailing, everything must be done under sail or via sculling oar. Given that at this point I’ve never sculled a boat in my life, we’re sailing off the mooring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was very calm in the morning and hardly any wind in the cove. Once we prepared Taleisin, I asked Annie if she’d prefer to be on the helm or drop the mooring line. She opted to drop the mooring line as it was less responsibility and something she felt was easier to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stored cheeky&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; on deck, hoisted the sails, tucked a reef in the main and Annie went forward to drop the mooring line. I pulled the sheets in, pulled the tiller over, took a deep breath… thinking “here we go”! The sails filled gently Taleisin picked up enough way and we started moving. I recall Annie asking, so when do we start sailing? My response was, we’re sailing now, it’s just very slow, but we’re sailing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We slowly weaved our way through all the moored boats and eventually made it out of the cove. We decided the previous night that we’d sail through the inner channel as it seemed like it might be more sheltered in case the weather pick up as there was a few islands that might provide some protection from the rougher seas. We had a glorious morning of easy sailing, the winds were light the water was smooth. I remember thinking, this is what life should be all about! Sailing is slow going, it’s great if you don’t have to be anywhere in a hurry! We removed the reef from the main and hoisted the big jib instead of the staysail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we sailed past Motuora Island things started to get a bit more exciting. The wind has slowly increased and we haven’t noticed as we’ve been running with it the whole way. The waves started to build. We don’t agree on the exact hight of the waves, but they were sufficiently big enough to cause Annie to get seasick. The swell was beam on, at no point did we feel in danger so we didn’t change course. Taleisin was just taking this all in her stride. Annie spent some time hanging over the lee rail. She eventually recovered and we sailed on towards the Whagaparoa passage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point We changed course towards long bay, the swell was now pushing us along and Taleisin was surfing the waves - this is a LOT of fun. Taleisin was very stable during this whole experience! After doing a bit of fun sailing we realised that we should probably sail around Devenport. I went down below to grab the ipad to verify our position and check out the charts on it. Due to the sea state I rushed back up on deck and I turned green very quickly. Now it was my turn to hang over the lee rail for over an hour. Annie did a fantastic job at the helm while I recovered. At this point we’re sailing towards Rangitoto Island with the intention of jibing once we pass Devenport. It will be an easy run into the marina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we got to Devenport I said to Annie, lets Jibe! So we went through the procedure, started to jibe… That’s when I realised that the wind was blowing a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; stronger than we realised. All of a sudden the heel was far more than we were comfortable. I yelled let the sheets go! Annie let the jib sheet go, I let the main sheet go, I pulled the helm hard over, Taleisin came back up right and I pointed her into the wind. I yelled out to Annie, get on the helm, keep her into the wind, I’m changing sails and reefing the main.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went forward, dropped the jib, dropped the main, put a reef in the main, hoisted the main and hoisted the staysail. That felt much better, less sail was a lot more manageable. Later we learned that the wind was 30kts gusting 35kts. I took the tiller, let Taleisin drop off and we started to sail again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here on out the sailing was actually pretty easy going. While about 30 minutes away from the marina I called the marina up asking the push boat to assist us getting into our marina berth. I was advised to radio once we get in and they will come and tie up next to us. When we got to the marina entrance we rounded up into the wind, I dropped the head sail, tucked another reef into the main. This was when I had the most expensive accident for the day, the jib sheet knocked my sun glasses off my head and I watched them sink to the bottom of the harbour - I had a fleeting thought about jumping in after them, but then realised that it was probably a very bad idea. I yelled some expletives (see I’m a real sailor now) and sailed into the marina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we entered the marina I got onto the radio and the marina boat met us about half way down the channel. They tied up next to us and we dropped the main sail. I made the mistake of thinking that the push boat crew would know what they are dealing with. Things got really exciting as they didn’t realise just how heavy Taleisin is. We had a few near misses with other boats, but eventually we got Taleisin all tied up. We sat down for a couple of minutes to regain composure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went down below, I grabbed my phone and gave Lin a call “Your baby is all tied up in Westhaven, all safe and sound”. I recanted some of the adventures and I could sense that she was relieved that we made it without anything major go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learnt more during that one trip than we did during a whole week’s worth of sailing lessons. We had to respond quickly, we had to think on our feet (something I’m fortunately used to due to my day job). More importantly we learnt that if things go wrong get yourself into a position where you can slow down, think, regroup and solve the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be remiss of me if I didn’t point out that this story mostly reflects the abilities of Taleisin and not that of our own. I’m convinced that if it was a lesser boat, things would not have been so smooth. We are indeed very proud care takers of this well found vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lin Pardey wrote her side of the story &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.landlpardey.com/june-2015-newsletter.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sailing-taleisin-for-the-first-time/&quot;&gt;Sailing Taleisin for the First Time&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Eben and Annie at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Taleisin - Adventure Machine!&lt;/a&gt; on October 22, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
